All right, welcome everybody to the
afternoon sessions. If you could quiet
down and take your seats, please.
All right, starting out this afternoon's
discussions, we have Wimbleu doing open
sage, next generation of agentic AI.
>> Okay, cool. Uh, nice to meet everyone.
I'm Wimbo. I'm currently uh assistant
professor at UCS Barbara, also a
research scientist at Met Times SL. Uh
today I will talk about our recent work
uh open sage uh which is a new agent
framework where we think could be the
future of a genti.
Uh before we talk about open s let's
look at the current agent world how
people build agent right. So basically
uh the idea is like there's
pre-specified
uh you know uh uh agent structure agent
topology and also two size memory
structure before you build agent. It's
kind of like you build a software you
know exactly what you want to build. Uh
you have a clear uh kind of like system
design and then we build an agent and
then we let agent run the job. But if we
dive in and think about uh the kind of
like limitation of this paradigm uh the
problem is like if we do presi pre
prespecified topology and also we
prespecify the set of tools that kind of
constrain the generalizability of the
agent a lot uh because we want agent to
do complex long horizon job uh but
sometimes agent may spawn its own uh you
know uh sub agent along the way of
execution uh along the way execution
agent may find out oh you know the set
of tool I have wrong uh is not enough I
need to invent or need to be added for
more tools uh to finish more complex
jobs uh so but if everything is
prespecified it going to constrain the
agent capability or generalizability a
lot uh so that's kind of motivate us to
uh design open s uh which we think is
what we call agent 2.0 prehance is like
agent 1.0 All uh so basically similar as
we designed the machine learning models
if you think about it like uh 10 years
ago or even like 20 years ago uh when
when we design machine learning models
the first step we're going to do is
feature engineering right so we need to
think about given a raw data what are
the features we use uh how to extract
feature size from the model from the raw
inputs uh and then there are so many
feature engineering methods that's kind
of adding our human knowledge age or
what we call inductive bias into the
model. Uh but then people turns out
found out you know we don't need that
step. You just trend the deep different
deep network model on the raw data. The
model will figure out by itself and
actually there without the industrial
bias constraint the search space of the
model. The model can actually uh you
know search for better uh like solutions
in a larger kind of search space. Uh so
that's kind of here we think about
similar uh what if we don't build a
agent uh what if we don't do all those
kind of like a manual feature
engineering like prespecified workflow
topology tool size what about we just
build a minimal set of scaffold that
enable the agent to build its own agent
right for example we enable some initial
tools for the agent so the agent know
you know along the way agent can spawn
its own sub agent design it own workflow
topology write his own tools or even
write his own memories so That's kind of
like the idea behind open sage is to
really unleash the power of AI when
building agents. Basically, we want
something like AI build AI uh agent
build agents. To do that,
sorry, it's not working.
Sorry, clicker is not working.
Okay, now it's back. So as you can see
what we want is we want to provide
minimal set of uh scaffolding that
enable agent to build his own agent
including write his own topology
workflow, write his own tools and also
design his own memory.
Uh so for the sake of time I skip the
technical detail. Basically we
redesigned the whole you know ADK what
we call agent design cookie uh to be oh
that's bad that's good uh to be able to
uh enable the agent to kind of explore
uh explore its own topology write it own
tools along with the way of execution so
here's a comparison between our open
stage uh with Google open all those uh
you know frontier agent developer kits
on this new capabilities as we can say
that's why we call open sage that's
agent 2.0. Uh that's really the kind of
like next generation of agent
construction uh framework that all this
capabilities freedom flexibilities
existing now existing uh ADK is able to
offer. Uh and then let's look at the
performance. Uh so uh so here we we main
uh kind of test open sage on coding and
also uh several security related
benchmarks. uh this is our performance
compared to cloud code and also uh
codeex by the time of we release open
sage that was about like uh February
this year. Uh as you can see on all
these existing benchmark uh like notable
benchmark like several bench swen pro
and the uh dialops gym open sage was
able to outperform all existing agent
frameworks. uh this number a little bit
outdated. Open Sage is still evolving.
Uh we are also kind of seeing new
performance on this benchmarks as well.
Uh and another kind of a recent trail we
feel very exciting is we actually run
open stage on the real world CTF game.
Uh for for those who know about it, we
run it against the Defcon 2026 uh
qualification game that's kind of
considered Olympic in the world of
offensive security. is most challenging
uh security uh kind of competition. All
there typically require a team of
professional hacker working on 42 48
hours like even sometimes there's team
with hundreds of hackers work on all
these challenges try to solve them. uh
what we do is that we try open sage on
15 of the non interactive uh challenges
because actually will not be uh uh the
organization uh kind of doesn't allow as
uh the you know AI to solve the China
submit. So what we do is we run in
parallel at the same time the Chinese
release. So u in total uh kind of 15 uh
challenges we able to solve seven of
them and after we do a post hawk
analysis uh four of them uh actually was
very close. If we give I don't know
another hour we can solve four more
challenges. Uh basically in total we
were able to retrieve eight flags and uh
put us on the top five in all the teams
that ever participate in the game. Uh
once the I didn't wrote here also very
interesting is open sage was able to
beat all the team that uh claim they
don't use AI or use low AI. Basically
this is the AI only agent that's able to
beat a team of hacker professional
hacker that didn't use AI in their
competition. So basically this shows
open sage was really able to solve real
world challenging task because actually
uh all these uh kind of uh computations
all these challenges uh we actually we
look when we look at the trace open
stage took like five or six hours of
continuous runs spawn like thousands of
sub aents to solve them. So basically
demonstrate open stage was really able
to uh scale up its own topology as able
to solve challenging tasks.
Uh now what are doing is like not only
the agent because we know like building
agent is the first step. Uh but the
brain the model itself also very
important sometimes model need to
co-evolve with the agent. uh this is
also kind of motivated by our
observation in the sense it's like if we
say run open sage with the latest model
we found that actually the model haven't
fully figure out how to build its own
agent sometimes model want to span new
agent but it actually fail so this
motivate us to bring up this kind of end
to end uh or more like you know holistic
framework where we think about we need
to build new agents to train a model uh
we need to basically train the model to
better span it own agent better write
his own tools and also we think about
the inference stack like the trajectory
of agent agent trajectory is actually
very different from pure QA task we also
are trying to develop new agent
inference frameworks but overall uh what
I want to deliver is like uh we
invention the future of AI agents is
really uh you know
the future of AI agents is really try to
open up the freedom to let AI do more uh
explorations in terms of everything that
eventually build up to the agent. What
we want is to provide meaningful
scaffolding, provide a powerful model,
provide most efficient inference
framework to make that happen. Okay.
Thanks.
All right, next we have Romesh Rascar,
professor MIT on the agentic web and the
bizarre era of AI.
Hello everyone. How's it going?
All right.
Fantastic. So for some time we have been
in the factory era of AI where some
large companies would produce these
products in you know large quantities
and we would just consume them. Uh but
very soon thanks to edge AI and small
models and things running on the edge
things running on your own machines uh
we're shifting to the bazar era. So a
lot of our work uh at MIT is about
thinking about when we'll have billions
maybe trillions of AI agents on the open
web what would the internet of AI agents
would look like and to motivate that
imagine a scenario where uh Sarah in
Texas in rural Texas has a health
condition she goes to her doctor John uh
and says hey I have chest pain I have
coorbidity and she's just not getting a
good answer uh from her doctors and Dr.
John can go on the open hive on the open
web and say hey listen for 100 bucks can
somebody solve the problem for Sarah uh
and when that happens uh billions of
agents all over the world wake up and
they say hey maybe I can take a piece of
this 100 bucks uh and uh you know they
can look at the data if it's related to
corresponding health condition uh start
training models also create a coalition
start collaborating with each other uh
and eventually maybe a handful of them
can solve the problem uh for Dr. John uh
and those let's say about 10 of them
solve together those 10 get paid out
from that $100 um and everybody else
kind of disappears uh and then
eventually Dr. John gets you know an
Expedia like answer of how he could help
you know Sarah the patient um and so
what's happening here is this not a it's
not like agents for e-commerce right
this is commerce that's possible because
of AI agents and Dr. John is not
accessing you know some kind of an
amazing health model AI model out there
but he's tapping into a network of
intelligence and that network is
available as a marketplace right this is
what we mean by the internet of AI
agents and the commerce for agents so
again we are kind of in the mainframe
era of AI kind of a factory era of AI AI
but very quickly we're shifting to the
PC era um some companies already you
know using agents within in trusted
boundaries, the internet of agents. But
very soon we'll shift to the internet of
agents where agents are, you know,
collaborating and and negotiating with
other agents that are well outside the
trusted boundaries. Uh but that's still
just for geeks how we can connect.
That's like the internet to go from the
internet to the worldwide web, we
needed, you know, HTML and browsers and
URLs and all the good stuff. And project
Nanda u that originally started at MIT
uh stands for AI agents in decentralized
architecture. Right? A mouthful. Nanda
for short means Sanskrit means joy in
Sanskrit but also name of my sister.
All right. So what does it mean to have
billions of agents out there? And if you
take this example I showed you of
commerce that agents will conduct. Uh I
think the closest analogy I can imagine
is highspeed trading. High frequency
trading. Uh and the reason why high
frequency trading works is we have a
bunch of things right. We have uh you
know there is a registry. You know there
is uh you know every merchant every
stock you know is is uh is
pre-qualified. You know there is
somewhat price transparency in how that
works. uh you know there is a way to
deal with fraud detection and so on and
all these things also had to be built
for the internet of AI agents right um
so this is a massive infrastructure
that's going to come together come you
know come get built for the billions of
Asians uh that are out there so any
anybody here like a openclaw fan here
right uh but you know openclaw is great
but it's only inbound it's only behaves
as a tool I cannot call your openclaw
agent it's like having a telephone that
can only make calls outside but can
never receive calls right so it's a
one-way
uh uh agent not a birectional agent so
the question is who's going to build
this infrastructure but a more
problematic way to think about this is
whoever builds this infrastructure will
also own it um so the question for us is
will we end up in a you know wall
gardens of this internet of AI agents or
will we get an an open and vibrant
and neutral and safe and scalable web
for AI Asians. So that's the mission for
us uh for for Nanda. Uh and we think
that there are four main bottlenecks. Uh
and if you can solve those four
bottlenecks, there's a chance uh we can
keep the agentic web as open as today's
internet as opposed to how we see on the
mobile phones like iOS and Android or
Facebook and Twitter all the wall
gardens. uh so the four bottlenecks are
you know a a I can DNS- like structure
second is passports and and
certification third is obvious which is
interoperability and fourth is at a
stationation so I'll go through this
very quickly and our group at MIT has
been working in this space for you know
last 11 or 12 years so we this journey
of thinking about what happens after
alexnet when we have billions of
individual you know AI systems that are
interacting with each other um and now
going forward within There are three
main research problems we need to solve.
Uh originally starting at MIT but now we
have many collaborators. The first one
as I said is like the DNS for Asians.
The second is knowledge pricing. We
think it's very critical that you know
data models inference compute all needs
to be priced you know just the way when
you hire a candidate we can figure out
their salary. Uh and the same way you
know we have to do knowledge pricing.
It's a very beautiful mathematical
problem. Come talk to us. And the other
problem is co-learning. You know the
last 14 years have been a fantastic
progress in machine learning but going
forward we think it's all about machine
co-learning about how two agents learn
from each other. Um, and when you think
about co-learning, you know, it's not
just about, you know, agents buying
services and transacting, but they're
going to form coalitions. They're going
to negotiate. They're going to compete,
you know, uh, for resources. Um, and
they have to achieve decisions, and
there'll be some alliances, there'll be
some betrayal, you know, it'll be like
the game of thrones among agents. Um, so
the other thing we need to do is we need
to have a starting point for the for the
web. There was something called Yahoo.
those of you old those of us as old as
me and Yahoo kind of created a safe
space to explore what the web is uh and
we need something similar to do that so
we created something called Nanda Town
so go check out Nanda Town off of MIT
website so it's kind of a sandbox that
allows anybody to bring enterprise
agents payments memory you know if
you're working in any of the spaces you
can come to Nanda town and explore this
extremely heterogeneous system and you
can have some ethical hackers there and
so on as well it's it's it's moving very
very quickly. So I enjoy I encourage you
to explore uh Nanda. Uh and then the
research of course works in multiple
directions you know uh Asian techch
devices you know this knowledge pricing
uh co-learning you know new forms of
Asian marketplaces and so on and of
course this is happening under a very
large tent that involves large companies
and startups uh and governments and so
on. Um and more recently we have this
series of hackathons called NandaHack
that are sponsored by different
organizations. So just go to
nandaack.mmedia.mmit.edu
to explore it. Now when we talk about
billions of agents we should be thinking
about at nation scales. Uh so what's
happening now is thanks to rather work
at Nandatown we're able to work with
very large ecosystem. So for example in
India uh we launched something called
Duth which means messenger uh and 1.5
billion agents uh that are not owned by
there's no corporate capture uh and that
run on the identity and payment rails
they already have city of Boston is also
launching with us you know a Boston
agent initiative uh and I I invite you
to come and talk to us about how the
civic agents are evolving as well and
what you'll quickly realize is that
today we're thinking about agents for X
you agents for coding, agents for
browsing, agents for, you know,
debugging, uh, agents for shopping and
so on. But we need to flip that and
start thinking about, you know, services
for agents, X for agents, infrastructure
for agents, compute for agents,
insurance for agent, you know,
healthcare for agents, education for
agents, everything that we do in the
society needs to be done for agents,
right?
So [clears throat]
I think the open agentic commerce is
going to emerge because uh intelligence
will be discovered uh intelligence will
be priced and intelligence will be
coordinated at scale. So come join us at
nanda.edu.
Thank you.
[applause]
Next we're introducing Shiva, principal
applied scientist, Amazon Web Services
towards adaptive agent frameworks.
>> Um,
good afternoon everyone. Um, my name is
Shivakashnatan. Um I'm a principal
applied scientist at AWS. Um me and my
team are working on uh developing AI
agents for monitoring and observability
for large scale cloud operations. And
today in this talk I'm going to share
some broad research directions that
we've been exploring to make agents more
adaptive.
So I think like let me start like
today's agents are already pretty
capable right. So we all know that how
how good they are good at planning uh
tool execution retrieving information
like iterating over the solutions to
come to solve complex tasks right but as
these agents gets deployed in more
mission critical applications we in AWS
believe there are some critical research
questions that need to be solved because
they can be widely deployed and here are
some of them that we have been exploring
in our team the first question that
we've been exploring is this question of
like how should agent assoc allocate
computational resources right imagine
that you have a fixed competition budget
and you want to agents to best utilize
the computational budget to solve the
problem at hand.
The second question is um along making
agents reason better right so agents
needs to be able to explore multiple
precinct paths to to make a decisions uh
in a more efficient fashion and the
third research question that we've been
exploring is the question of how do you
evolve agents over time right so the
agents are not static pieces but that's
continually adapt over time to make and
learn how to solve the task over time
better so in this talk I'm going to just
focus on the first two task but I'll
just briefly end up with how we are
solving the looking at the third problem
at the end.
So let me start with the direction one
like so this is the notion of like
budget aware adaptive execution right so
so today if you look at most most agents
they have a fixed execution policy that
you define using a prompt or like some
other local heristic right I guess what
our goal is to to make these agents
learn these execution policies so the
agents can learn over time these
execution policy so that the a and and
then they decide what how these policies
are then executed and like then you also
have notion of like a computational
budget like you want the agents to work
best under some computational budget
right so abstractly you can think of
this as a problem where you have some
context the agent has some context and
it is to decide the best next action to
do uh the action could be like a re
information use the tool verify the
results update memory whatever like
there is some action space and then and
the the important constraint is that
there is notion of budget right I mean
so there is a budget that agent has and
it has to respect that budget while
while uh executing C tools Right.
So again like I mean if you think of
this like a little bit more like I think
this can be like phrased as like a um in
in terms of formulation it can be
phrases as a constraint marker decision
process and we've been using this
framework to uh to learn these policies
right so again the goal is to maximize
some kind of expected utility under some
notion of subject to some computitional
budget right again the budget could come
from latency cost token whatever you
want to think of like some notion of
budget right and does it work and yeah
the answer is yeah I we've been had some
success in implementing this. Um so what
we've been showed that like this plot
like on the on the plot on the right
hand side um shows these adaptive agents
learning better execution policy than
using a scale riser word model which is
commonly used in in practice. Right? And
on the on the the other plot on the on
my left side is is showing that it's
also more sample efficient. Right? So
you're you're reaching the same
competence uh using fewer iterations. So
the the amount of samples you need to
get to some level of competence is
significantly lower if you use these
kind of adaptive execution policies. If
you learn these adaptive execution
policies
okay the second direction that I just
briefly want to talk about is notion of
parallel reasoning right so so today we
have these agents or at least these
models which are following a single
reasoning path right and we have been
exploring ideas that allow models to
explore multiple reasoning paths in
parallel. So these these parallel paths
are kind of learned during training and
not during inference time and then they
are coordinated um to select one path
right. So the answer is one. So there's
some coordinated reasoning that happens
uh at the end which takes these multiple
reasoning parts and produces one answer
and again we have been implementing this
ideas and testing it on benchmarks and
like both our mathematical reasoning and
coding benchmarks we have been getting
consistently good results like and this
these are some results on like um some
maths and coding task and you can see
the results for pass one to pass K we've
been getting better than like very
strong baselines.
And especially the results are
impressive on K equal to one which is
like like the one shot one when we get
this one result out.
Okay. So like maybe like I'm almost out
of time. So I just want to finish by
going back to the research questions
that I was introducing. So we have been
like I just mentioned about this budget
aware adaptive execution where the goal
is to learn an execution policy that's
adaptive and best uses the constraints
it has. And then the question of the
second question of par reasoning where
you're trying to generate agents to have
multiple reasoning so that multiple
reasoning paths so that they explore
multiple paths to solving the same
problem. The third question that we have
been also been focusing is this notion
of continual model or agent adaptation.
Again the goal is to come up with
principal postraining schemes uh that
can adapt to new task. Um the the main
challenge there is to make sure that you
when you learn the new task you don't
forget what you learned previously,
right? And we believe that these kind of
like these solving these kind of three
research directions is will help us to
generate the next generation frontier
agents. Thank you.
[applause]
>> And next we have Tanya Rusta joining us
virtually. She's director of AI AMD a
Berkeley alumni speaking on information
retrieval in the age of agentic AI.
Try again.
>> Uh, can you hear me now?
>> Yes.
>> Okay, great. Third time is a charm. Um,
hi everyone. Um I'm Tanya Rusta and uh I
work at AMD as a director of AI. Sorry I
wasn't able to make it in person but I'm
glad uh at least we have Zoom. I will be
spending the next few minutes discussing
uh evaluation framework for uh agentic
IR.
So uh let's start with the shift.
Basically what has happened in the last
few years is that we have moved from
traditional information retrieval
classic rack where you had this straight
line of there is a query from the user.
The search engine would get the
documents, come up with a rank list,
rerank it, and then present the list to
the user. Um to this more of an agentic
flow where the agent actually uh does uh
you know planning, tries to figure out
what the intent of the query is uh does
the search, gathers the results,
analyzes, critiques and then presents
the final result. So this means that the
unit of work has basically used from uh
has moved from uh lookup to an ongoing
conversation with the world.
uh and this agentic uh IR shows up in
the deep research agents uh as most of
you have uh seen uh with chat GPT and
you know other uh agents that you're
able to put a question out for example
here is the question is about
cholesterol medication and uh the agent
basically tries to understand you know
what the intent of the question is then
it goes and uses uh various tools to
gather
um the websites, you know, different
information, price information, uh drug
interactions, etc., and then, uh comes
up with the answer, uh tries to ground
the answer into um you know, retrieved
evidence and then finally presents the
results to the user. And this basically
saves um us many many hours and uh
having to kind of go through all the
document blog posts etc and trying to
figure all of this out on our own.
Uh and a lot of times this kind of
agentic IR is now taking over
potentially 20 turns. So it has become a
multihop thing.
But uh here's the uncomfortable uh gap
that still uh sort of exists and that is
that when we want to kind of uh evaluate
these um you know agentic IR we still uh
tend to look at the final answer use
scores like blue and rouge to see if the
final answer is correct and um given the
now the information seeking is really
interactive multi-turn it has this
temporal aspect it has to be evidence
driven uh simply grading the final
answer doesn't work very well. Uh so
what do we do? We basically have to look
at uh the uh trace and start to um you
know look try to um assess the
correctness you know of every hop you
know was it adequate to answer the um
user the cost in terms of number of
tokens latency etc and in terms of uh
where the field is heading I would say
there is the reasoning aware retrieval
so now not only you have the keywords
from the query You're looking at the
agents uh trace reasoning traces. There
is the multi-turn hop aware benchmarks
that are being uh developed like MTRA.
Uh there is the retrieval um you know
graph uh rack uh so that you know you
can look at the relationships. There is
self rack to cut through some of the
whole hallucinations and adaptive rack
to basically uh route you know queries
based on their complexity and effort.
And finally actually looking at the
number of tokens that um are used um you
know and optimis optimizing around that
um as a metric for information
retrieval.
So what I want to leave you with is that
you know our information seeking has
changed. The agents have changed how we
get information. And that means that we
have to also change the way we assess if
these agents are doing the right thing
and if they're achieving the goal that
they have set out.
And that's uh all I have. Um thanks for
having me.
Thank you, Tanya. And next we have
Dennis Akiro, senior staff AI scientist
with Service Now, speaking on our small
LLMs ready for coding agents.
Hi everyone.
waiting for slides. So actually uh this
is a
a bit of a personal story. So few months
ago I was uh uh flying transatlantic and
realized that um as AI scientist I can
be very inefficient without a a coding
agent while disconnected from internet.
So, uh, I realized that maybe I should
develop my own local coding agent and
see if a local LLM running on my MacBook
can actually h handle realistic uh, uh,
coding agentic tasks.
Uh, oh yeah, uh, there is a link to this
repo. So, I just open sourced it
recently. Um and uh you can also see the
presentation there. Um
so um [clears throat]
uh this agent is called ask me and uh it
does one small thing at a time. So uh
it's it's basically designed around
three ideas key ideas how to minimize
the context that we pass to a small LLM
because LLMs are not really good when
you pass them a lot of um context uh for
small uh language models running
locally. And uh the second is that um we
do very small actions at a time and uh
immediately verify that action. And the
third thing is uh we minimize reasoning
as much as possible only use it on
recovery loops when things go wrong.
So uh here is an example. Uh you give a
small LLM. Uh so in this example it's
quen 3.6
uh and um basically you want to just
create a small program
think of a hello world compile it and
run it but the thing fails because
actually it compiled it into a temporary
directory but it needs to execute from
another directory. So things like this
are much harder for small lms to
realize. So we have to make very very
small changes and verify them one at a
time.
So uh around this idea we basically
develop a loop. So ask me is a very
minimal loop. It's just one file. It
used to be 1,000 lines of code. Now it's
like close to 2k lines of code. And uh
so yeah uh basically you want to
minimize uh um number of uh big planning
steps you take smaller steps and only go
back when uh things go wrong.
So uh I evaluated this uh on uh few
hundred tests and here uh this is just
smoke tests with a uh two families of
LLMs Gemma 4 and Quinn and basically um
it works except uh one Quen model. This
was just a sanity check that we can use
it. Uh and then next is actually running
realistic uh tasks. So this is actually
building feature for an app and uh what
I realized is that uh um that basically
the these agents can do most of the
work. Uh uh but the issue is that uh
they fail to verify their work and have
this uh full loop you know observe what
happens go back and solve it. So
basically it passes most of the tests
but not all tests for developing an app.
Uh and it's the same story across both
uh Quen 3.6
and uh Gemma 4.
And uh for the record this was run on
open router not locally because locally
it will take me ages to run this and um
there is a limited memory on my MacBook.
Uh next uh so uh I think uh basically
this wasn't an example uh just creating
a small agent uh uh running locally with
minimal hardness and uh it shows that it
can uh basically work locally with a
very small LLM doesn't need a large code
base like codex or a cloth code uh and
um yeah you can look at uh results and
uh how it works in this repo. Uh I guess
I also want to give some shout out. So
uh I actually compared it against PI
harness which is the most minimal
harness that people use at the moment.
Uh it's much more efficient than codex
or cloth code. And uh I I also did some
comparison with open hands and basically
this is a even smaller than both those
harnesses for working with very very
small LLMs locally. So and it's still
work in progress. Uh there is still like
a lot of issues. Uh but yeah, I'm happy
to uh receive any feedback, any
questions you have.
Thank you.
All right. And now we have professor uh
Neu uh here from UC Berkeley on agentic
uh or agent reasoning requiring
compressing information into executable
reasoning structure.
>> Thank you. My name is Nio. I'm
co-founder and CEO of a company called
Across AI. I'm also a professor here.
What I'm going to talk about today is
that basically the whole problem that
we're all solving and have been solving
for years now is compressing
information. Because at the end of the
day, that is what a model does. That is
what a harness does. We are finding
different ways to take lots and lots of
information and compress it into a
format that is executable. Like a
transforming model is executable and
predicts the next token. Now, over the
next few years, what's going to happen
is we're going to come up with more and
more architectures that are able to do
this in more complicated ways. And one
of the first problems that we're going
to have to solve is what are the various
types of processes and what is the
optimal architecture or harness for each
of these processes. I want to share one
that we've had a lot of success with,
which is uh reasoning graphs. A
reasoning graph is a graph of agents. So
each of the circles that you see in this
graph is is one of the agents and we've
identified that for particular processes
specifically processes that need to be
run repeatedly and with very high
consistency. This is a very good
architecture to do that. So the way this
works is that at the very bottom layer
you have a layer of agents that just
connect to all of the different systems
where the raw data lives and all these
agents do is understand that raw data.
Then you have another layer. These are
the layers of agents that do the
reasoning. And then finally, there's a
layer of agents that take the right
action at the right time. So any path
that goes from the bottom all the way to
the top is one possible reasoning path.
And we've seen different flavors of the
same idea come up today. Like you could
run these in parallel. You could
optimize them in certain kinds of ways.
Now the question then becomes how do you
create one of these? And uh we've seen
also this idea show up in a couple other
talks today as well. Um, and it has to
be that it's done by an agent. So, what
we're going to see more and more is
these uh sort of handshakes between an
agent and a harness. So, and that agent
is trained to know very well how to work
with that harness. And these different
architectures are going to be good at
different kinds of processes. So, one
that we've been working a lot on is this
architect agent that works with
processes that run consistently and
highly accurately like financial
processes or supply chain or something
that a company needs to keep running
over and over is non-deterministic,
still needs to be intelligent, but needs
to be highly consistent and explainable.
So, what you get is very high
consistency. We've hit routinely above
95% accuracy in running these processes
in examples or benchmarks where even
Fable can only hit about 40 to 70%
accuracy. And we also get very high
speed. No custom code is being written
in any part of generation of this
harness. It's all the architect agent
working together with this particular
harness. So we can launch new use cases
in a matter of weeks. And the most
important part of this architecture is
the compounding intelligence and the
weights of that model.
So every time the architect takes a new
use case and creates a reasoning graph
for it and learns how to do that, it
gets better at doing that. So this is
this kind of a model we're going to see
more and more and we're going to see it
for different kinds of processes. I
wanted to give you one example of a
process that we uh identified using this
architecture and that's invoice
matching. So very very large companies
receive lots and lots of invoices and
they have to make a very simple decision
pay it or don't pay it. They receive a
certain amount of fraud, so they can't
pay everything. They also can't sit on
it too long because if they don't pay an
invoice in time, it affects the rest of
their supply chain. So imagine large
companies are processing millions of
these invoices every month. So an
invoice is received, it has to be
matched to a PO. It has to be
normalized. There are lots and lots of
exceptions like the units might be
different, the currency might be
different, there's tax in certain areas.
One example that I stuck in my head
which I thought was very funny is that
if it's um liquid, it's okay if the
amount on the invoice is up to 5% less
than what was on the purchase order, but
only during summers because some of it
evaporates and there's nothing you can
do. So the agent has to keep learning.
It's not a one-time oneshot learning
thing. It's also not something that
happens just in one session. It's
something that lasts a process that
lasts long horizons, months and weeks.
And every time you see an exception, you
have to learn from it. A baseline agent
harness even using Fable here only gets
about 40% of it right.
This is what the reasoning graph that we
built where our architect agent built
for this process looks like. It's made
up of lots of agents, their wiring,
their instructions, what models each
agent should use. Each has their own
long-term memory. So all of these
decisions, all of these engineering
decisions are made by the agent. And
what we hit was 99.9% accuracy on this
real data example. um the first graph
was up and running in a week and in 96%
of the cases not only did we give the
right decision but we were able to
correctly explain why that decision was
made. This brought down the cost of
processing those invoices at this one
Fortune 500 from $5 an invoice to one
and a half in this example and more
recently this week we got it down to 10
cents per invoice. So those are the
kinds of um advances that you can make
if you are able to take take that
learning and compress it into a reusable
structure. Thank you.
[applause]
All right. And now we have Johan Shyler
Smith, uh senior staff engineer for
Temporal speaking on systems foundations
for Agentic AI.
Hi everyone, I'm Johan Schlersmith. I'm
at Temporal Technologies and today I'm
going to be talking a bit about our
perspective on the agentic AI landscape
and introducing Temporal as well. So
just by show of hands, who here is
familiar with temporal? Maybe has heard
of it? Okay, we've got a few. How many
people have actually used temporal? All
right. Well, I'll tell you, uh, this is
going to be a highlevel overview. If you
stay past this session, we're also going
to be doing a workshop where you can get
hands-on and get into the code. So,
let's, uh, just get into it and let's
talk about systems. So, when we talk
about systems, we're talking about
creating some sort of functionality by
putting together a whole bunch of
components. And in the case of AI, there
are a lot of these components. And so we
need to get that functionality. But in
addition to the core basic
functionality, there are these sort of
crosscutting concerns, right? Things
like reliability, which temporal has a
really a deep experience in um
efficiency, security, evolvability, that
includes the scalability. Uh it includes
the ability to do upgrades and so forth.
Let's dive in a little bit on
reliability because this is uh really
sort of explains the core mechanisms
underlying temporal. So suppose we have
an agent. In this case, it's uh a
customer service agent that's going to
be helping with returns. And so this
agent needs to connect to a whole bunch
of different systems, right? Knowledge
bases, inventory, ERP. It needs to
handle payments. It needs to probably
have escalations. It needs to be able to
send emails. And in order to make all of
this work reliably, what do we need to
do? We need to put retries in a whole
bunch of different places. We probably
need queuing to handle load. Um we need
state management to keep track of the
process. all the way through. And these
are all places where things can go
sideways. And so, whoever is building
this needs to account for that one way
or another. Now, traditionally, software
interleaves the application concerns,
the business logic with the systems
concerns, things like reliability and
other systems concerns that we've talked
about. Now, fundamentally, you know, if
there's one thing to take away from this
talk about what temporal makes possible
is it's this model of of durable
execution. And what that does is it
allows you to write code that puts the
system logic over on one side and the
application concerns on another and
really isolate that out. Now, the
temporal uh open source project itself,
what it lets you do is it lets you build
crash proof applications. It's open
source license, so MIT license and you
can back it with um a number of of
different databases like Postgress or
Cassandra. There's also a cloud product.
But the key thing about it is that it
lets you write regular code, regular
programming languages, right? Python,
TypeScript, you name it. Um and get
crash proof execution. So how do you
recover after a crash? Well, there's
basically two ways to get that state
back. You can either save it or you can
recomputee it. And with temporal we give
you, you can think of it, and we'll get
more of this in the workshop, but simple
annotations that you could put on the
code and you could say, "Here's what I
want you to recomputee. Here's where I
want you to save state." Okay? And then
that's sort of if there's a trick,
that's the trick. Um, there's other cool
things like distributed systems from
ordinary language primitives. This is
pretty cool. Um but uh I I want to talk
for a minute uh about how uh companies
out there, our our users, our customers
are using temporal. This is Venat, VP of
uh application infrastructure at OpenAI.
And so one application that's notable is
chat GPT images where there's a whole
series of steps that need to happen.
They need to all happen reliably in
order to spit out that image. That was
one of the the notable use cases that
for temporal and open AI uh codecs on
the web is another one. But really
there's a whole slew of things ranging
from the infrastructure control planes
uh to the the data connectors that's
effectively think about that as building
and maintaining the the rag indexes and
so forth. And then finally traditional
business processes
uh and really across the ecosystem
whether it's at Nvidia or at uh cursor
now SpaceX or um uh lovable replet
uh temporal is being used really across
that stack to enable agentic AI. So now
I want to dive in and just make a few
observations about really sharing how we
think about it and what we've learned
from working with companies across the
ecosystem. So we have this functionality
that we're need to provide right it's an
agent and that means different things to
different people definitely in a
business context it's basically some
system that gets something done right
and what we spend a lot of time thinking
about particularly in the AI foundations
team which is the team that I'm on is
really what are the right abstractions
what are the tradeoffs that come along
with a sentic AI workload um how do we
slice them which ones do we pick a point
in the space um where do we maybe give
you a knob for
And so just a few uh observations about
these workloads that I think are
particularly interesting. I'm not going
to read through all of this, but um you
know just on the LLMs, right? So this is
also I'll just say you know it's it's
really it's a different different
workload from other workloads we've
needed to deal with before in systems.
And so we really it's really fun to be
able to sort of rethink these um
abstractions. So non-determinism, right?
So that means that you call into an LM
you're going to need to validate and
store those responses. Um, but it's also
interesting because it has this flip
side where it's also uh sort of fuzzy
and it's actually forgiving with respect
to its inputs. That's the sort of other
side of the coin from its outputs not
being necessarily um 100% determined
security. This is um interesting from
the threats side. So you often think
about adversarial inputs, things like
prompt injection and alignment, but also
a great threat model when you're
thinking about uh agents is is actually
just um bad judgment, right? because it
like it happens that RM-rf
um and so that's driving a lot of our by
accident right not not thinking that's
driving a lot of our design
considerations and then certainly from
the execution profile the fact that
you're interacting with a world that's a
place where you want to capture your
state you want to make sure that that
you're there you know writing things
down carefully um and also bursty load
which calls for serverless and so forth
now uh another observation that we've
made from working with companies
throughout the ecosystem is that there's
really this spectrum of agency and that
the right solution for a particular uh
application for a particular
functionality could come from anywhere
across the spectrum and actually the
more agency you have it's not always a
better thing. So when people think about
agents oftent times they're thinking
about this sort of level three which is
an you know an agentic loop the LLM
makes all of the decisions about what
happens next. But if you go over to the
left, you look at level one, there's
actually a huge number of applications
um something like summarization or so
forth where the job actually gets done
really well by having regular code drive
the control flow and having those LLMs
inserted at very specific points, right?
Could be very reliable and if that gets
the job done, then that's probably the
right solution. The other end of the
spectrum, we go as far as self-evolving
agents, which we now see in in some of
the harnesses. And so there's there's a
reason for that, but you can also think
that's probably not also the the right
solution for the job. And when we think
about abstractions at Temporal
Abstractions for Agentic AI, we're
really thinking about being able to
allow you to dial that in and to frankly
go back and forth along this spectrum
without rewriting your entire
application. And so one thing that we
are sharing today is the temporal agent
harness. So this is not yet a supported
product, but if you go and you start the
the GitHub repo, then hopefully it will
be soon. I'll put up a QR code in a
second to that as well. Um, but this is
a set of abstractions built on top of
Temporal's core durable execution
abstractions that make it easy to build
uh practical agents for things that you
know, whatever it is that you want to
build. So we give you that ability to
plug in the inner harness, which could
be a coding agent like open code. could
be something like open eye agents SDK
which also has a lot of interesting
sandboxing functionality pedantic AI any
of these we've really worked hard to
embrace this ecosystem you can plug your
tools and again this is really designed
to give you abstractions to mix and
match whether that means you want to
talk to it through Slack through teams
uh you name it so this is just a a quick
screen grab of what was an open code
session I was in there just fixing a bug
in a simple program and because I've run
that with the agent harness. Not only am
I getting the the durability, the
reliability if I wanted to run this at
scale, but I also get sort of for free,
but frankly, it's part of the package. I
get the observability, the ability to
dive in and see what was the agent
reasoning about, you know, at at the
various steps, what were the tool calls
and um uh human approvals and so forth
that happened along the way. And that's
the benefit that you get from really
being thoughtful about the abstractions
that you're bringing into uh to your
agentic AI. So with that um I'm finished
here. I welcome you to stay in this room
for the next session which is going to
be a workshop where we're going to get
hands-on with temporal. Thank you.
[applause]
All right. And you're welcome to stick
around and Got a line with Nikolai who's
going to step through building AI agents
to survive failure.
on the online sessions.
>> Um,
let me just move this. Um, I probably
won't have Q&A, but yeah. No. Um,
but
There will
Hey everyone. Oh, sorry.
Hey everyone. How's everybody doing?
Everyone doing good? Um, I know we've
all been sitting around for a while
listening to a bunch of very exciting AI
lectures. So, I want to do things a
little bit different and put a little
energy into this room. If you all could
please stand up with me, please, and
participate in my small little fun game.
I promise nobody will be hurt.
Um, so everyone, thank you for so much
for getting up. All I want you to do is
to find two people, give them a high
five, look them in the eye, and tell
them you're freaking amazing.
You all are amazing.
There you go. Love the smiles on the
face. Yes. Look at that. Continued. Love
it. That's it. Thank you guys so much.
And one more thing for social media. I'm
going to do a little selfie video with
all of us. When I say go, just I'll do
something crazy.
>> Go.
[cheering]
>> That was so lame. We got to try that
again. Can you guys like 5x that,
please?
>> Ready? Go.
[cheering]
>> Look at that. That was an afford. Love
that.
Hey everyone, my name is Nikolai Lotkin.
I am a staff developer advocate at
Temporal. Um, I am also a dog dad and a
roller skater. There's a little preview
of my cute little baby Mia. She's a co
baby.
Um, so today we're going to talk, we're
doing a workshop. So, this will be
hands-on. So, if you got a laptop and
you want to do a little coding and
playing around, that's going to be
awesome because this is ultimately I
love workshops where you guys can
actually leave with some value doing
something, learning something. The best
way to learn anything is actually to be
hands-on and not just passive listening.
You'll retain way more information. But
my goal is to cover four topics. We
probably won't get to all of them. It's
a lot of information, but it's okay
because afterwards I'll give you the
GitHub repo and you can pursue it on
your own should you decide to. Um, we'll
do foundations of agentic AI systems.
We'll build one. Um, then we'll build
with an agentic framework which is uh
open AI agents SDK. We'll do a human in
the loop and then we will orchestrate
micro agents. These will be uh multiple
agents talking to each other. All of
them are going to be via durable uh
durable which is what temp using
temporal which is exactly what Johan
just talked about will actually make it
work in real time together.
So um what is an agentic loop? Well an
LLM right an LLM can reason about um
context that we provided. What LL an LLM
lacks is the ability to take action
whenever
um it doesn't have enough information.
And so an agent loop ultimately provides
an LLM the capability to take action
outside of itself should it need other
information. And so what we can see here
is um we can start an agenda loop with
some instructions and goals. Um you can
define some information from it. for
example, you're a travel assistant, uh,
find a flight to Miami, ask for
confirmation before booking your
payments. With that context, we pass
that information to the decision maker,
which is the LLM that will start the
agentic loop. Um, the LLM will decide,
does it have enough information or do I
need to call a tool and if I don't need
any of that, do I already have enough
information in order to provide a final
answer? If it doesn't have enough
information, it's going to call a tool.
Tools are what we define and tell the
LLM to use, right? I'm sure many of you
all have used uh codeex cla you'll see
it calling different kinds of tools.
Those tools are defined by the
harnesses. Sometimes they're defined by
you. You provide the tools tell them
tell to the LLM that they exist. The LLM
will decide when to use those tools. Now
using those tools it'll decide uh it'll
get an output and then it'll decide does
that output give me enough to give you a
final answer or do I need to continue in
this loop of gathering more information
until I can comfortably provide an
answer and that is ultimately the
agentic loop there's simpler versions of
it there are more complicated versions
of it um ultimately you define Before
we actually jump into building one
ourselves,
I'm very curious.
If you would all just scan that with
your phone and um you can answer it
whether you know temporal or not. I'm
just super curious of the layout of the
audience here. It will allow me to
tailor the workshop better to fit your
needs.
I hope most of you at least have heard
about it because I'm here on stage.
No, I'm joking. But
cool. This is kind of like what we've
experienced so far. Yeah. And feel free
to drop emojis as well. The flying
emojis are super cute.
Oh, cool. All right. You guys mostly
have not heard about it or heard about
it but never used it. Okay, beautiful.
So, this workshop will be very advanced
for a lot of you all that have never
used it, but um I will do my best to
walk you through it and like I said,
you'll have the code afterwards to
enjoy.
Okay, so Johan mentioned this a little
bit, but ultimately temporal allows you
to write code as though failures don't
exist. What that means is you're going
to focus on the business logic of your
agents of your distributed systems.
Agents are distributed systems, right?
whatever you want to do, you put that in
a workflow, which is what we call it, a
step, a sequence of steps that we want
to execute. And then you pull out your
non-deterministic steps, your API calls,
your LLM calls, your data based queries
into what we call activities. When you
wrap those activities inside of our
SDKs, we support all the most popular
SDKs, Python, TypeScript, Java, Go, um,
Ruby, and so on. When you wrap those
activities inside of our SDKs, we create
a history of all of the activities that
have been performed up to a certain
point. Whenever any kind of failure
occurs, we pause at that point in
history and we will wait for that
failure to be resolved, which can be
seconds, it can be minutes, it can be
years. When that failure is resolved, we
proceed with the rest of your operations
as though a failure never happened.
What's even cooler is that waiting for
us to proceed with those operations
actually doesn't cost you any resources
because we've recorded that all in our
history.
And so this is kind of what interacting
with an LLM can look like. Um you'll see
the workflow. The workflow is what we
will wrap our entire process under.
Right? that will involve ultimately um
calling the LLM uh starting that LLM
process invoking it and then proceeding
with whatever steps we need. In our very
simplest case, it's just going to be um
asking it a question. In more
complicated cases, when we do human in
the loop, it'll involve asking it a
question, waiting for user feedback, and
going through the entire human in the
loop sequence. Um and so all of that is
wrapped in what we call a workflow. The
non-deterministic pieces we wrap in
activities. These are the parts that can
fail. You want that inside of temporal
because we will make sure that those
pieces never fail. By the way, temporal
has six nines of reliability.
Um, and so in our entire workflow,
what can fail? So many things can fail,
right? Calls to the LLM due to network
reliability. Actually this morning I got
a 429 uh being rate limited by OpenAI.
Um API calls can fail, rate limits,
services go down, AWS goes down. Um all
of those being wrapped in an activity
will allow Temporal to pick up from the
failures after they are resolved.
All right, cool. Less talk and more
coding. So let's give our first demo a
try. Um what you will want to do is
navigate to that URL please. It on your
computer this is not for phone because
you'll be doing a little bit of coding
less coding but you'll be doing a lot of
interactivity. Um navigate to that URL.
It will take you to an instruct
environment which is basically a virtual
lab. No uh setup required and there's a
bunch of exercises and I will walk you
through a bunch of them step by step and
along the way we will learn some things.
Everybody has that link?
Yeah. Anybody not at the link yet that
wants to be at the link?
Anybody not at the link yet that wants
to be Okay, I'll wait. Hold on for a
moment.
Ultimately, yeah, I I think it there
might be a form. Just enter your
information and then it'll start booting
up a workshop. It should be max 90
seconds for the boot. So, proceed. Click
the start button. Wait for the 90
seconds. I'll show you what the screen
should look like afterwards. It's in
It's in a Docker container, so 90
seconds is almost as fast as we could
make it. Everybody at the right place?
Anybody not at this URL yet?
Beautiful.
Your place that you arrive to should
look like this after about 90 seconds.
Show of hands. Anybody here yet at a
place that looks like this?
Not yet. Okay. What? One person. Anyone
else? Oh, beautiful. Yep. I'll wait for
all all of you to get here
and I'll walk you through this first one
uh together very patiently and then the
next ones they will uh progressively get
more and more difficult.
Let me zoom in here.
Oh, and I have fun quizzes along the
way. So, pay attention to things that I
say and things that you do.
Um, show of hands. Who is here now?
Who is at this place?
Oh, and I also have at least I have
three fantastic TAs. Um, they're over
here in the front if you need any help.
And I have Melanie in the back. If you
need any help, raise your hand. They
will come by and help you out. Before
raising for help for hands, who is at
this point now? Got one. Please raise
your hands high so that we can proceed.
We only got three or four people.
Okay, five people. Okay. All right. I'll
proceed slowly while you guys boot. Um,
and if you need help, raise your hands.
RTAs are sensational.
So this is the instruct environment.
Pretty much everything has been uh
created here to make it easy for you to
write some code and also interact. Each
of these tabs that you will see these
blue buttons, they're clickable. You can
click on the worker tab. It'll cl take
you to this terminal. This will take you
to the starter terminal. We have the
temporal UI which is where our workflows
will show up. We have a network control
panel that will allow us to simulate
network failures. For example, turning
off access to geoloccation, IP uh APIs,
IP address and so on. And we have our
code editor which is where all the code
will show up.
You guys will do work out of the
exercise folder. The code will be
relatively simple. It's Python code, but
it'll be really simple. You'll basically
just be uncommenting some code to make
things work. But if for whatever reason
you stumble inside of the solution
folder, there's an exact layout
structure. You can just navigate to that
folder and it will show you the solution
to the challenge.
[snorts]
Um let me see what else I need to show
you all in here. Oh, and since this is
our first exercise, we can walk through
it all together. Um so here we can see
writing the agent part. We'll click the
editor tab which will take us here and
then it tells us to go to exercise tools
workflow.py.
In here we have our temporal workflow.
You'll see we have a bunch of imports.
We're importing OpenAI agents SDK.
We're importing some tools that we
created. Ultimately, these tools are
just web requests to different
endpoints. This is a web request to get
coordinates. This is a web request to
get IP address, location info, and
weather. Um, all of these exist right
here in tool activities. You can see
here's our tool calls, which are
ultimately just um functions. You can
see we've wrapped our tool calls and
activities so that they become durable
and reliable.
[snorts]
We give our LLM a system prompt. Whether
this is a great system prompt or not, we
can debate later. [snorts]
And here begins our workflow. Uh we defi
we provide a workflow definition.
And here we start our workflow
execution.
And inside of our workflow, the these
are going to be the business operations
that we want to perform. The steps that
we want to execute in order to perform
whatever we want to perform. We can have
one workflow, we can have thousands of
workflows, it doesn't matter. It's the
steps that you'll want to perform. Um,
in this case, your goal, as you will
see, there's a to-do statement here. It
will tell you exactly what to do. Since
this is our first one, I'm taking us
through this. Little by little, I'll
reduce the amount of handholding I
provide. So in this case, it's really
simple. We will uncomment this agent so
that we can see how to construct it
within our workflow. So I'm just going
to go down here, uncomment. I recently
got really good feedback on this
workshop from one of our customers that
not everyone is familiar with VS Code uh
keyboard shortcuts. It's command slash
to uncomment. And if you're a Windows, I
don't know the command for uncommenting.
I'm so sorry. Um, and so we uncomment
our agent. We can see the setup. This is
using Open AI agents SDK. It's our
integration with them. All it does is
call out to the Open AI APIs. We just
put a beautiful wrapper around it just
to make the code cleaner and easier for
you to use. Provide a name. Give it the
system prompt. Pick the model. GPT40 is
good enough for this one. Provide our
tools which are self-created. Uh API
endpoint calls. Right? Remember these
tools can be just web requests. It could
be uh calls to MCP servers. Um could be
so many options. We provide these tools.
We're providing them as activities tools
meaning that they will be wrapped inside
of temporal durability.
And so every one of them if it ever
fails will get the durability behind the
scenes or in front of the in front of
you as well. And then ultimately we'll
run the agent and return the final
output. So let's see if we uh performed
everything that we needed. Uh we did
this step. Uh that's pretty much it for
this one. Very simple. Now we want to
execute
uh our process. The very first thing we
want to do is spin up a worker. So just
click on the worker tab. Click this run
button. No need to even copy and paste
in here. It'll start a worker. The
worker is the process that will keep
pulling um our task Q to decide what
work it needs to perform on our behalf.
Right? We may have a backlog of things
that need to be performed. Uh the worker
is the thing that uh pulls the task Q to
see what's in the backlog to execute.
Once the worker has started, um, we can
do our starter.
The starter is exactly the code that you
just saw, but we're just starting the
workflow. And in this case, we're simply
asking our LLM, what is the weather in
Tokyo? And so, we will execute this by
going to the starter tab, hitting run.
It will ask the LLM this question, and
we will see how it responds. to see how
it responds. We'll navigate to the
temporal UI. We'll do a quick refresh
and our workflow already completed.
Let's open it up and see what happens.
So, of course, this is using our Python
SDK. As I mentioned, we have many. This
is one of the really cool things about
Temporal. Um, I'm I'm totally new to
Temporal. I didn't even know about it
until I started working at this company.
But one of the things that I really love
is the visibility that we get to track
every single interaction that's
happening within our workflow. So for
example, you can see the entire
timeline. Here we invoked the model
activity. Here we got the coordinates.
Here we invoked another model activity.
Here we got the weather. And then we
invol invoked the last model activity.
We can click on these and see exactly
what happened. We get a bunch of
information. Uh we can see the headers.
We can see the input that was provided,
right? And so you can kind of see what
was the input that we sent to OpenAI in
order to make this happen. Of course,
everything that we uh showed in the
code, but then also everything that was
also abstracted away so you don't have
to deal with the things that are not
important. So here's the input and we
can see its output as well. If you
scroll down here a bit, this is the
result of that web request. Um, and so
this is what happened. It came back with
a response ID and blah blah blah. less
less important here for example. But
what happens when we called our get
coordinates activity.
So um here's what it sent into the get
coordinates which was just Tokyo. And
here's the output that it sent uh got
back to us. Tokyo longitude and latitude
and so on. Get weather same thing. Um
here's the input using the longitude and
latitude that we got from Tokyo. And
what's the output? It gave us the
information. It gave us the weather.
Let's see what the weather is there. Um,
looks like temperature 79.6 degrees
Fahrenheit. Uh, it even gave us the wind
speed and so on. And ultimately, of
course, we can see all of that inside of
our CLI because that's what it came back
with, 79.6 degrees Fahrenheit with a
light wind speed. Um, let me see if
there's anything else valuable to cover
here.
So good so far. Show of hands. Who was
able to successfully run their first
workflow? Oo, love it. Awesome.
Congratulations. Great job, everyone.
All right, we'll make it a little bit
more fun.
We will break it and actually simulate
durability in real time. In this case,
navigate to the network control panel.
This simulates real failures. It'll turn
off access to different kinds of APIs.
In our case, let's go ahead and turn off
the weather API, right? You can imagine
either your network is blocking that
call, maybe you work in an enterprise
and they don't want you to talk into the
weather API, maybe the weather API is
actually down, maybe AWS is down, hence
the weather API is down. Um, so it's
off. Now, let's do the same exact thing.
Um, we will come back to our starter. We
will run the same query, but in this
case, it looks like we're asking what is
the weather in London. And of course,
you can switch it up. In fact, we can
make it we can make could have made it
even more fun and said what is the
weather in uh UC Berkeley? But we can do
that next. We run it. Now, let's go back
to the temporal UI and see what happens.
This is the cool part because this is
where the durability comes in. First of
all, you'll see that now it's in running
state and it will stay in running state
until the problem is resolved. You will
see over here this call it keeps
retrying and it will keep retrying
depending on the default retry policy
that we've defined. In our case, we have
a default retry policy. We didn't
explicitly specify anything and so it
will keep retrying forever. There's also
automatic backoffs
um and backoff coefficients that exist
in here as well. Right? Give you guys an
example. You don't want your um LLM for
example to pull an open AI API all the
time because right that'll cost you
resources. And so maybe if you made 10
calls, you want to wait for 10 seconds
before you make another 10 calls. And if
those 10 calls fail, maybe you want to
wait for 30 seconds before you make
another 10 calls. And so that's called
an exponential backoff. And so that's
already built in here automatically.
Normally, if temporal doesn't exist, we
got to code this logic ourselves. We can
get a it can get a bit hairy, but
because of temporal, this is what's
happening. And so you'll see the last
failure service error 503 service
unavailable.
Um, and so that's what's happening.
and it'll keep keep retrying based on
the criteria that we define. We can
define it explicitly should we choose so
because we have some specific business
requirements or we can leave it in its
default state which is exactly what
you'll see here. So let's fix the
problem, right? Let's imagine AWS had an
outage. It's back up. Weather API is
back up.
turn the weather API back on and within
a few moments we should see this recover
as though no failure ever occurred. We
don't need to touch any code. It'll pick
up exactly from the place where the
failure happened. No extra resources
have been utilized. The workflow will
finish it correctly. We can go back to
our terminal
and we got the weather uh from London
which is right there.
who has been able to successfully
replicate that. Fantastic. You guys are
so good.
Um, let me see here if anything else I
want to show you all before we move on.
maybe just one thing to point out to you
all here. Um, because this is using
OpenAI agents SDK, you can make your own
you you can make your own agentic loop
for sure. A lot of the uh agent
frameworks they hide the gentic loop
behind the scenes but ultimately it's a
while true loop where you do the exact
operations that I mentioned you wait for
user input decide whether that user
input uh decide whether you have enough
information to make a decision if you
don't have enough information to make a
decision what do you do you call tools
or do you do something else um you could
do that all yourself which
will probably be about 50 lines of code
in this case it's just one line of code
um we're using activity this tool in
order to provide the durability to all
of the tools that we are calling. Um,
and then we're using uh the SDKs. Um,
here you pretty much define everything
on your own. So like this would be a
self-made agentic loop that would exist.
This is using the OpenAI agents SDK. You
just do runner.run run and then uh
OpenAI agents SDK handles the loop for
you behind the scenes. You just pass in
uh the agent and the query.
Uh here's the lines of orchestration
code that you would need to write
yourself should you decide how to work
with the agentic loop. Uh here is again
uh the SDK replaces all of that. the
durability should you want to uh execute
the workflows. Looks like that. Um,
cool. That looks good to me.
Everybody good on this point? Show of
hands if you if that makes sense.
Beautiful. All right, let's uh we can
hit
um we can hit skip and move on to the
next. There'll be another module. It
might take a few seconds to load, but
let it load while I have a fun quiz for
all of us.
Please join our fun game. There will be
quiz questions that we answer and
there's a little leaderboard that we can
compete on. And maybe for the top three
people, we will give away some swag. So
afterwards, I'll grab your information
and the top three people will get some
swag from us.
>> Yeah. Join.
Uh oh. while while people are joining.
Um these question questions are single
choice or multiple choice. Some answers
will have multiple responses.
Um and the faster you answer the more
points you get.
But of course getting the right answer
is also important.
Oh, love it. You guys are awesome. So
many people participating.
This is my first ever public workshop
for temporal. So I'm super excited to
see all of you guys participating in
this. Thank you. All right, everybody
joined. I'm not seeing any more people
joining. All right, we are beginning.
You snooze, you lose.
I have cool music here that's playing. I
guess you guys can't hear it.
Hopefully most of you guys get this.
This one should be an easier question.
All right. Congratulations to the 41
people. Yes, the LLM decides which
action to perform next. Ultimately, the
LLM is the decision maker. We pass it
context. We tell it tools. The LLM
decides whether it has enough
information
um and what to do next, whether to call
more tools or to give you back a final
response. All the other stuff is just a
distraction.
Demo two is the one we just did.
I hope like 99% of you guys get this
right.
All right, great job. Uh, yes, in this
case, we're we didn't write any loop.
Um, I showed you how a potential loop
that you write can look. In this case,
we're using OpenAI agents SDK. The loop
is written for us inside the runner.run.
This one I might not have covered too
well. I'm so sorry. Hopefully some of
you caught it as I was going through the
workflow, but I should have done a
better job of covering it. But let's
see.
One of the answers is definitely not
right. The other two, it's like, yeah,
maybe.
Yeah, good job for those of you. Yeah,
it was could could have been one of
these two. Um, it's invoke model
activity. If we uh look at
here in the next section, oh crap,
because the I don't have the workflows
in here. I'll show you all next time
when we get back in here. It's invoke
model activity that is called
This is like our core
reason for existing.
Is this a hard question? LeBron is
unhappy about this question. I'm sorry,
LeBron.
Yeah, great job to the 41 people. Um,
the reason why we wrap uh open AILLM
calls or any LLM calls in activities is
because they're non-deterministic. And
so any nondeter deterministic code, we
want to have an activities so that we
can replay that afterwards. Um we want
to keep the deterministic code which is
just the business logic business flow
inside of the workflow non-deterministic
parts put that in activities um so that
we can replay them when necessary.
All right we will come back to this
after the next section. Oh man I am so
short on time. I think I got like 22
minutes. All right. Um show of hands.
I'm going to offer you guys two options
of what you what we can cover. We can
cover human in the loop or we can cover
multi-agentic
processing.
People for human in the loop
people for multi-agentic processing. All
right, we'll do multi-agentic
processing.
So for that um
skip skip this demo four human in the
loop. The next one will be multi-gentic.
We'll skip this one.
I knew the hour would fly but again I'll
share the repo afterwards and um you all
can follow this workshop along and dig
into it as much as you want. And then of
course we're all here. We have a Slack
community, temporal Slack community. You
guys can reach out to us there for help.
And then you can find me also on
LinkedIn and I'll be glad to help you
all as well. Um let's proceed.
We'll skip human in the loop then. Sorry
all the human in the loop people. Um
orchestrating micro agents. So so far
what we've done in our workshop which
has been really fast. We have an LLM
which becomes an agent right uh because
it runs in a loop. uh we've given it
some tools. We didn't give it an MCP
tool in this workshop but we can had we
done the previous chapter we also would
have added a human in the loop tool
which is ultimately uh allows us to ask
and wait for human feedback right for
human in the loop you can wait for an
approval you can wait for some kind of
information that's chp GPT is a human in
the loop uh type of thing right how does
it wait for you to respond to it before
proceeding with the next operation um
but this is becoming very busy
And so we want to break this up. That's
when we're going to create multi-gentic
processing. Many a few reasons why we
want to break break that up. I'm going
to fly through this because we're I want
to make sure you guys get hands-on.
Context poisoning, distraction, context
clash, and confusion all can lead due to
having too much context. Right? Maybe
for a smaller workflow it's simple. For
larger workflows, more data, the more
stuff we provide, the harder it is for
the LLMs to reason about.
So, we're going to break this up. We're
going to have tools. Um, we're going to
have a weather agent and a Formula 1
agent that we're going to call and we're
going to have a personal assistant
agent. Our personal assistant agent is
going to be the entry into the entire
process, our chat GPT. And then using
our query uh our chat GPT aka personal
assistant agent will decide which tools
it wants to call whether the weather
agent or the F1 agent or maybe both or
maybe more.
[snorts]
Um few ways to call our sub agents. We
can call them via an activity.
We can call them via a child workflow.
You can imagine you have one business
process that's running.
Maybe you put a decision process in
another you you you put the
decision-making logic in another process
which we call a child workflow. So you
can have the main workflow starting a
child workflow or you can do that via
Nexus which is our other technology that
ultimately allows you to segregate based
on
uh team domains. You can segregate based
on uh regions. You can segregate based
on security concerns. You can segregate
based on uh code requirements. Maybe you
want to have one agent being deployed at
a different frequency than another
agent. This is a massive topic, but if
you guys want to know more information
about it, just Google Nexus and then
you'll learn more about it. But you'll
see it being used here, but I won't
cover it so much in depth.
That's what that looks like. Cool. Let's
actually build it. So, at this point,
you should be at this step, which we're
calling demo five. Um, and all of the
agents existing in their own workflow.
So, make sure you get to demo five.
Let's start it
and I will let you work your way through
this. It's ba Oh, no. Let me uh quickly
work you uh the architecture. There's an
architecture diagram that I've added
here from one agent doing one thing to
three agents existing. Now, there's a
lot going on. Um,
this architecture diagram is kind of
meant to help you connect all of the
pieces. I'll quickly quickly walk you
through it so that everyone can be
hands-on. Um, we start here at um the
personal assistant workflow, right? As I
mentioned, personal assistant will
capture all of the information and we
ask the personal assistant to query
what's the weather for the next F1 race.
The personal assistant will then decide
what do I need for that to to happen. We
have F1 tool uh which is a Nexus
operation that will call our F1 agent,
right? It'll execute in a separate file
uh using a separate task q and it has an
entire process that it will follow here
in order to execute this here. We'll
walk through it. I'm not um these do all
of these steps. Ultimately the F1 agent
all it does is call to F1 MCP server
which we're hosting but it's just uh
calling ultimately to the F1 APIs. All
that information makes its way back to
our personal assistant agent. Now it
says, "Okay, do I have enough
information or not?" At this case, no,
because we also wanted to know the
weather. So now it has to call the
weather agent. So it's going to call the
weather agent as a child workflow. Um,
again, I'm we're doing all of these
different operations just to show you
guys the different possibilities. Of
course, we can code this in whatever way
makes sense. Um this child workflow as a
tool will be a separate work uh workflow
running on a different task q using a
different agent that will go through
this process of deciding what is the
weather in the location that we want.
And so in this case it'll call our get
coco coordinates activity. You've seen
that it'll call our get weather activity
also tools and ultimately those are just
public HTTP requests that gather the
information and bring it back to our
weather agent which will bring it back
to our personal assistant agent.
With all of that information, the
personal assistant agent can now give us
a final response and say at the
Singapore Grand Prix expect 30° C. That
is what we are building here. Of course,
more complicated than this, but I leave
it to you all to now give this a shot.
Step through here. It should not be much
more difficult than what we did, but
follow along. You'll wire up the
orchestrator by going in the editor and
um uncommenting some code, and then you
should be able to run it on your own.
I'll give you all like one minute and
then I will do this myself with you all
so I can work walk you guys through the
important parts.
I'll start slowly walking through here
and
yeah, we'll go in the editor,
go in the exercise folder
inside we we have a lot more files. You
guys can see how quickly these things
can get super complex. And so hopefully
you guys are kind of understanding how
complicated it can be to manage a
distributed system.
And this one is tiny.
Um we'll navigate to our personal
assistant.py file which exists right
here.
Again, if anyone needs any help, we have
sensational teaching assistants here
that can help you. They are way more
intelligent than I am.
[snorts]
Um, very similar layout to what you guys
have seen before. This is a personal
assistant. Gets a system prompt, get
some tools. Here's the workflow
definition. Honestly, like getting
started with temporal for me the biggest
challenges were number one understanding
the
model of how it works which is like okay
if I want to orchestrate anything put
the process in a workflow and then think
about like okay what what are all the
non-deterministic things that I'm doing
pull those out and put them in
activities which are just functions
right put those in functions and then
put those functions together in a
sequence in the workflow. And so once
you overcome that gap, the rest of the
stuff becomes really cool and really
easy because all we do is code for the
happy path. We just tell the system to
do what we want it to do. The failures
will happen along the way and temporal
will just be there like holding the
queue for us, holding the history for us
until we decide to proceed forward. So
in this case, we're going to uncomment
the weather tool block.
That's what this is. Previously,
remember our weather tool was just a
function and be called an API. In this
case, we're going to call it as a child
workflow. It means the personal
assistant workflow will start a new
workflow and they'll be tied together.
I'll show you how. Give it some
information. Um,
in the second part, we're going to
uncomment our F1 tool. Our F1 tool is
ultimately
um
a call, an API call. We're we're going
to call it through Nexus.
Nexus you can basically think of as an
API
that whatever team wants to expose and
the team of course can expose whatever
they want. If I want to expose to you
only certain endpoints that you can call
to maybe another team or maybe another
organization, you can call those
endpoints only and that's it. And that's
what what makes this really nice is you
basically provide the endpoint.
You provide the name of the service and
using that information, the workflow can
call that endpoint and whatever happens
behind the scenes, we're going to call
an F1 API. It could be many other things
that happen behind the scenes. Those
things can even change, but this
contract will remain the same ultimately
allowing the caller to not have to
change their code. But behind the
scenes, if you want to improve it, we
want to move to version two and so on,
we can.
[snorts] And then we give it a tool
description.
Let me see if anything else. Here's our
personal assistant agent. and make sure
that the tools are included inside of
our tools object.
And then we continue running it as as
before using runner.run and so on. That
looks good to me. Let me see. We
accomplished everything. Fantastic. Now,
because we have multiple
uh
workflows, we're going to use multiple
workers as well. So let's spin up our
personal assistant worker.
You can imagine all of them as uh
separately deployable units. Our
personal assistant worker is running.
We can start up our F1 worker.
Run that.
[snorts]
Let's go to our starter. Let me see what
um okay we can do this call and then we
will ask when is the next F1 race and
what's the weather there right now and
run that and this is all real of course
calling out to real APIs
now it's running let's go to our
temporal UI and see what's happening
refresh there we go we got two workflows
that are executing uh we got our
personal assistant and remember we
started a separate workflow for asking
for the weather. Let's go inside the
personal assistant and see what it's
doing in here.
Inside of the personal assistant, we can
see the input, right, which is the
original query that we got. And we can
see the output because it's already went
through the entire process. Tolds us
that the next F1 race is in the Dutch
Grand Prix scheduled for August 23rd.
Um, and the weather is 64.7 degrees
Fahrenheit. Here are all of the steps
that it executed. Um, here's a call to
Nexus. We don't need to dig in dig so
deep into that, but it basically allows
us to call a totally separate, you can,
as I mentioned, you it's basically
calling an API and behind the scenes,
the API performs its separate things. We
can see it here, Nexus link. We can
click on the Nexus link, navigate inside
of that Nexus link is another workflow,
the F1 expert that performed its own
operations. Here's everything that it
did. gathered the F1 data, called the F1
API, returned that data back.
And then the personal assistant
workflow,
um, weather agent workflow
called the weather agents, gathered that
data and then returned it.
And then using all that information, it
was a able to res give us the answer
back. Now we can try to break it.
I'll give you all a moment to break it,
but ultimately
you can just turn something off. Let's
turn off the weather again
[snorts] in the network control panel.
Turn off the weather and go back to our
starter. Rerun it. But we can uh yeah,
this is fine. We'll rerun this query
again.
We'll go back to our temporal UI.
We'll have two workflows executing.
Clearly, they're not going to finish.
Let's see where it breaks. It's going to
break at the weather agent workflow,
right? You can see that now this is here
and it's continuing
and it's going to continue running
until the issue is resolved.
If you co go back to our ask weather
agent workflow, this is what's happening
here. This call of get coordinates is
the one failing and it will keep failing
until the issue is resolved.
Let's fix it.
Turn that back on.
Go back to the temporal UI.
Both of the workflows will start up as
soon as they realize that the API
endpoint is back up.
Give him a moment. Um, the restarting
depends on the retry policy
and
exponential
um
exponential backoff, right? Sometimes we
might get to a point where we have to
wait for like many seconds before
something is retried because we've been
waiting for something to happen for a
long time. There we go. Both of them
completed successfully.
Cool. Who here has been able to
successfully make their agents fail?
Beautiful. All right, let's wrap up with
the quiz. Hold on. That means I have to
skip a few questions.
Get back on your mobile phones.
Oh, here's the leaderboard for now.
Let's see.
YB is rocking it with Vargasi at a close
second and Ming at a close third. Let's
see what can happen with the results
after this quiz.
You guys get in here. Is everyone in
here?
Bunch of people joining.
I love the sm the emojis. Keep going.
Bunch of people joining. Join, join,
join. Who's going to get the swag?
Who wants the swag? How badly do you
want this swag?
I know. Everybody wants swag. We'll do
so much for Swagen Coffee, right? We'll
do like anything for Swagen Coffee.
All right, I think everyone's good. Oh,
Vargasi joined. We needed Vargasi in
there. He was number two, I think.
We still have people joining. All right,
let's go.
Let's see. You guys should be good with
this one. Ah, no. Ask weather agent.
That's not a specialist. We had child
workflow tool. Um,
using as a temporal primitive, but it's
also on me. I didn't do the best job
covering it because I had to rush. I'm
sorry. Let's see this next one.
So this is if we didn't uncomment
the tools inside of the tools object.
What do you imagine would happen? We
have the workflow
but the tools have not been added.
This one is tricky.
tricky for beginners for sure.
Let's see.
All right. Yeah, it was it was a hard
one. Um the activity will still run. We
just don't have the tools to call. The
the workflow will still start. Um but we
don't have the tools to call. So, um
it'll just return with invalid
information.
>> [snorts]
>> I definitely talked about this. What is
the value
of getting the workflow execution
of getting the workflow execution and
wrapping those specialists in those
workflows? You guys saw it in the UI
what we get.
One of them is definitely not.
Let's see.
All right. Yeah, great job, guys. That's
really good. Yeah, you get all three.
You don't get more RAM. Sorry. You got
to pay for RAM on your own.
One minute. All right. This will be the
last question. I got one minute.
Yeah, this one is hard because it's
Nexus specific, but basically instead of
calling one workflow from another,
remember what I told you Nexus is like?
It's an API. So what does an API give
you
that controller that direct imports in
your code don't give you? [music]
All right. Yeah, you guys got some some
of these really good. Yeah, you don't
get extra operations. APIs don't do
anything for that namespace consistency.
That's on the developer to define.
Beautiful
friends. That's it. I'm being kicked
out. Um all I ask from you all are two
things. Please follow me on LinkedIn. I
will drop all the content that you saw
here um on there so you can get it. And
then number two in your in your instruct
there's your feedback tab. Please just
give us some feedback so that I can use
this to improve the workshop for the
future. And give me constructive
feedback um that I can act on. You can
tell me I suck. No big deal. But please
tell me why I suck. I would love that.
Um, and then also the winner. Oh, let me
let you all scan that. Everybody scan
that.
And let's check the three winners of the
quiz.
All right. And the three winners are
Anton, Henrik, and Ming. I'll be in the
back. Please see me after. I got you
guys with swag, okay? I'll be like right
in the back of the room. Thank you all
so much. Have a beautiful day.
>> [applause]
>> All right.
Thank you for the great workshop.
Now we're moving on to continued talking
sessions. Uh we have DOA principal
applied scientist Microsoft with mindful
agents human inspired memories for long
horizon tasks.
>> I did not last.
>> That's okay. No worries.
>> Hello everyone. It's great to be here.
Um I'm from the Microsoft Fabric AI team
and I'm here to talk about the work
we're doing in the real-time
intelligence space on our longunning
agents. uh where we take some
inspiration from ourselves as humans to
improve the memory so we can get better
at accomplishing tasks.
Um so in the space that we're working at
uh we tend to have longunning agents
that has access to uh data that's uh
high volume streaming data is high
volume and to just like set up the
problem that we're dealing with and the
motivation for the approach that we're
implementing here um I kind of want to
contrast it to how we as humans uh store
memories and um how like we tend to have
the situation for our agents instead. So
as humans uh we're not we have like
storage constraints. So what's likely to
happen is we because of that constraint
we will tend to the limit makes us
better at distilling memories. So for
instance, recently uh I was on a train
ride in Europe and you know as you're on
the train you look outside the window
and you pass by you know endless fields
and you see some maybe windmills you see
some animals grazing and we don't have
the capacity to necessarily remember
every strand of grass or every bit of
thing over there. Uh what we're good at
is being able to distill that
information and just remember
interesting things that might be
relevant to us. Um and this is just
something that we through evolution are
good at. Uh whereas if you think about
the agents, we don't have that problem
in terms of the storage constraints. Uh
we can log every bit of information um
somewhat like relatively cheap and we
can log every trace and what we do is we
capture retrieve and typically we
summarize and retain the summary. Uh so
over time we are with summaries of
summaries of summaries uh which
typically works well um until you know
at the time of retrieval when you're
looking for something very specific uh
for most cases but for the case that
we're working on uh we're interested in
getting agents that work with these like
big volume data sets and we want them to
be proactive. Um so what we worked on is
we are working on building a memory life
cycle as a feedback loop for our agents
where we have a system uh that starts
with first ingestion where uh we
basically ingest all of the data from
the observability substrate and then
what we do is consolidation uh which is
kind of like similar to the idea of
sleeping uh but what we do is we ddup
merge uh and we try to consolidate all
of the memories that come to become
candidates. And the idea in here is
while this is similar to maybe humans,
uh the consolidation cycles for the
agents that we're working in are domain
dependent and they might not always be
temporal. Uh so I don't know how many of
you were are still in the room, but you
were just building an agent that was
like looking at F1 for example. So if
you're a uh person like if the agent is
working on Formula 1 races the telemetry
that you take during the race will be
very different from what happens after
the race like during the race uh race
days versus the off week and then it's
going to be very different from the
season. So consolidation doesn't
necessarily mean it has to be daily uh
but you need to process in some batch in
some cadence. Uh next we have a
forgetting where there is decay and
interference and the idea is we want to
make sure that if we have all these
consolidated memories that are uh stable
candidates we want to make sure that we
end up remembering the important things
and all the unimportant stuff uh gets
forgotten or most of it as best as we
can and then the next stage is
retrieval. Um so for the retrieval what
we work on is a hybrid way where we have
these memories stored in uh the cold
storage where we know a domain and put
them in a graph but uh we also have the
live data coming in and we want to make
sure that the agent can access both the
streaming data and what's in the storage
that's more stable and be able to uh
determine what's the best memory to use
at the time. Um so that gets us to the
uh feedback cycle where
at the time of the retrieval you will
have usually conflicts. So something new
might happen and it might conflict the
memory that you have established that
became stable in the cold storage. Uh
that's where maturation and
reconolidation comes in. Uh because we
don't want to necessarily keep adding a
new memory over and over into the graph
that's very hard to retrieve from. So
you need to determine whether you want
to update an entity in the graph. Uh
whether you want to up like add a new
entity to the graph because there's some
new information that's important or uh
maybe discard what's the live
information that's coming in because
it's erroneous.
So what like next I kind of want to talk
about all of these bits have uh are
there like each their own components
with different optimizations that you
need to make. So I want to chat a bit
about how we approach our evals for them
and how like our thinking around it. Um
so here is two uh cases where we
evaluates kind of like the ceiling on
the floor about the best case scenario
and the a very tough scenario where on
the left side uh we're having a
retention benchmark which is more uh
deterministic where in this case we are
looking at a case where the system has
clear labels of everything that's
important. So what we were looking to
optimize in here is like how often we
want to consolidate and what's the kind
of the cadence we want to use for it.
And for this case that we were looking
at and this changes from domain to
domain but uh it's things started
stabilizing around 500 events at a time.
Uh sorry I think 200 events at a time.
It's kind of small to see from here for
me but let's see. Yeah 200 events at a
time with a precision where if we like
forgot over it uh that got better. So
like we're checking it what's the best
precision you get with how much you
consolidate how often you consolidate
and then how much for getting ads over
it. Uh in the next next case we were
using a retrieval benchmark utilizing
long map eval where we were looking at
um how much compression should we have?
What's the optimal storage size we
should look for uh without being
destructive. So this is an uh eval where
it's conversations. So we have no labels
about what might be important or not
which is not the ideal case for the type
of work we're doing because um the like
the idea that we have is these domain
experts that do repeated tasks and
there's an idea of how you can learn
what's important but even then uh we can
like optimize and there's a trade-off
between how much you want to compress
and what accuracy you get. So with that
um the kind of like approach in more
general is for the type of memory work
that we're doing um we need three types
of evaluations and they kind of have
like different um ideas about what
they're looking for. So one of them is
retention uh which can be a quick eval
on deterministically if you're building
a memory system and if you want to keep
the important information can you just
like make like can you make sure that
what you're keeping is actually
important versus not which is you need
the labels for it and there's a lot of
work that we're doing on like how we get
better labels but then the next one is
retrieval. So assuming that you built a
good memory system, then you need to
look at how well you're retrieving from
it and are you getting the memories that
you're looking for in that like great
system you built because if it's hard to
navigate your memory and it's how hard
to do the retrieval part of things then
that still like is necessary but not
sufficient. So you want to have good
retrieval and finally uh you really for
the agents you want to look at your task
completion evals um which are the most
important because it's closer to the
user. If the you might give the best
memory to the agent and depending on how
you uh how it's exposed to the agent in
your harness, the agent might choose to
ignore it and still might not accomplish
the task. Uh and this is kind of like
the most expensive one for because
because for the longunning agents, it is
kind of expensive to build and run the
evals, but it's the most important. So
like for each component, we're focusing
on these three things. Um, so to kind of
just sum things up, um, logs are not
memories. And I think like where things
are going is like for longunning agents,
uh, you want to make sure that you have
more than just the traces that's going
to become available to them as memories.
And the the way like the volume works to
be efficient, you'll have to uh figure
out how you keep the important things or
not. Um and then another important point
is the domain is important and like for
these cases it needs to be predeclared
and depending on how well you can do it
uh at the runtime you need to have it
prior otherwise that affects the um
efficiency and accuracy of the agents
that you're running. Um so in terms of
kind the next steps we're working on uh
we're working with the foundry Microsoft
foundry team on end to end evals uh in
state bunch and we're also doing some
work on like better work on domain
learning and uh graph ontology where the
idea is what we found in a lot of these
is the way you set your graph structure
and the ontology for it has a big effect
on your accuracy in addition to these
components. So we're working on them. Uh
so with that uh thank you very much and
I look forward to meeting everyone
after. Thank you.
Now we have Ian Fischer, uh, CEO of
Bodic, an optimization perspective on
recursive self-improvement.
>> Okay. Uh, yeah, my name is Ian Fischer.
I'm co-founder, co-CEO of Poetic. Uh,
and Poetic, if you haven't heard of us,
uh, is a startup we founded about a year
and a half ago that's entirely focused
on recursive self-improvement. So, we're
building AI that improves itself. Um,
and in the past year and a little less
than a year, our focus has taken us from
from nothing to a system that
automatically can set state-of-the-art
on a a wide variety of major public
benchmarks. um were were 10 scientists
and engineers mostly from Google Deep
Mind and Apple, Microsoft, Amazon, by
dance. Uh some of our early results uh
we had on reasoning and uh knowledge
extraction setting state-of-the-arts on
all these uh and and coding. Uh so let
me dive into this. I want to define
carefully what RSI is. Uh and so you
know should be really simple. There's
only three letters. Uh and really two of
them are doing all the work here. So
recursive uh means that the new
improvements at each step are going to
drive the next round of improvements. Uh
and self is the system really is going
to improve itself, not some other
target. Uh improvement is really
obvious. Everything, you know,
everybody's doing improvement of some
sort. Uh but RNS really come together as
a pair. Uh if you don't have both of
them, uh you you really aren't doing the
right thing. Uh and the reason that I'm
being a little bit pedantic here is uh
that common use of RSI is both u too
permissive and too restrictive. Uh so
some people have described approaches as
as being RSI that are really just a
standard iterative improvement loop. Um
and other commentators other people uh
think that RSI is something is only RSI
if you are improving the parameters of a
large language model. Uh and this is too
restrictive because there are a lot of
other pieces of of an intelligent system
that can be improved uh quite
effectively. Uh and so why does RSI
matter? uh we think that this is you
know RSI is the most important frontier
in AI research because uh the
improvements of real RSI systems
compound uh and this is going to lead to
super intelligence much more quickly
than than human-driven improvements are
likely to achieve for you know the
obvious reasons that that humans don't
become inexerably smarter while
improving models but RSI systems can
uh so I'll talk a bit about the the
landscape here we can um uh split RSI
approaches on two axes. Uh on the y-
axis going from cheap at the top to
expensive at the bottom and on the
x-axis going from things that really
aren't RSI just standard of it iterative
optimization approaches on the left to
uh uh things that are RSI on the right.
Uh and so you know the upper right uh
quadrant here is a a nice place to be.
Of course we put poetic there uh but
that's not arbitrary. We we put
ourselves there because our loop does in
fact compound. It really is RSI and each
step of RSI only costs an inference run
rather than a training run for an LLM.
Uh in the lower right are where the best
funded efforts are. This is what people
generally think of uh when they're
talking about RSI. Again, the kind of
this LLM centric perspective where
anthropic, OpenAI, and Google uh are
putting a lot of effort and these are
generally genuinely RSI, but they do
require to train an LLM from scratch at
every step. In the upper right, we have
a few neighbors, and they're they're
also genuine RSI, and they're also
cheap, but they're a bit narrower than
our approach. um like Darwin Girdle
machines and uh and Sika are both
targeting coding primarily and uh the
Miniax harness um trains on some of its
own generated data. Uh so as I mentioned
you basically you can you can partition
this uh this landscape into two pieces
and on the bottom we have LLM centric
approaches that focus primarily on
improving a particular LLM uh and uh
then on the top we have more
systemsoriented approaches uh that view
the LLM just as a component of a broader
system that should be improved and
shifting from an LLM centric approach to
uh view to a a systemsoriented view uh
opens up a lot of possibilities for
improvement that you that you would
otherwise miss. Also, they tend to be
faster and cheaper. So, I'll I'll talk a
little bit about two of the uh really
prominent approaches. Uh one is uh what
the recent anthropic post uh AI that
builds itself describes where um you
take a version of cloud, you uh put it
inside of cloud code and then humans
plus cloud code improve cloud. Uh and so
this is uh partial RSI uh um clearly you
know clearly there's a you know claude
is part of the uh system that's being is
the thing that's being improved and it's
part of the system that's that's
improving it uh but there are humans in
there so I kind of don't want to count
them and anthropic doesn't count them
either. Uh on the right we have another
common uh approach called an automated
AI scientist. This is similar also to
auto research and this is typically not
going to be RSI. There's a there's a
number of nodes here um that are doing
different things but basically you know
you generate the system generates a
hypothesis uh and then it implements
that hypothesis and then it measures it
and then it like writes a paper about it
and puts that paper back into some
knowledge store and this is
not you usually is not targeting a piece
of its system itself. So, it's not
actually going to be RSI. Um, but we can
make both of these into pure RSI
systems. Uh, in the case of anthropic,
we can just get rid of the humans.
They've kind of indicated that that's
that's where they're headed and uh
that's maybe something that they're
worried about. For the AI scientist, uh
it's also a simple fix. you just uh
target the LLM that you use in your um
ASI excuse me in your in your AI
scientist loop. Uh of course doing that
makes it uh much more expensive than
what most people are doing with
automated AI scientists. Um so what does
poetic do? So what we're doing is what
we call selfoptimizing optimizers. Uh so
what's this look like? We we start with
a general purpose optimizer. uh where a
general purpose optimizer is uh one that
doesn't rely on rely on any specialized
signals like gradients. Um uh it just re
requires measurable feedback from the
optimization target. Uh so this is more
general even than like blackbox
optimizers like hill climbing um because
it doesn't have to be uh you know
quantitative um in nature. So then given
that optimizer that general purpose
optimizer let's use it to optimize
something. So we'll have some
optimization target. Uh it's providing
feedback to the optimizer. Uh and as I
said the the feedback here can be quite
arbitrary. So you know it could be
standard approaches like accuracy costs
things like this. Uh or more unusual
feedback like rubric evaluations or
reasoning targets. Um so once we have
these two pieces this clearly is still
not RSI. Um this is just a standard
iterative optimization but we have this
uh this uh framework of a general
general purpose optimizer that we can
then apply to the optimizer itself. So
now the optimizer is optimizing the
optimizer that's optimizing the
optimization target. Uh and this is now
RSI.
So in order to have an optimizer that
can optimize itself, you only need two
things. it needs to be a general purpose
optimizer and the optimizer needs to
provide feedback about his performance.
Uh so since we started with a general
purpose optimizer and every optimizer
can do that uh we don't have a problem
here. Uh but this is you know I I want
to be clear this is very different from
saying that the optimizer is atom or SGD
right that would not work. Um so this is
what we call the poetic meta system. uh
it is uh RSI and we use it to optimize
everything. So every task that the meta
system optimizes helps it optimize
itself. Uh which makes it become a more
powerful optimizer. Uh and again since
it is a general purpose optimizer, we
can point it at any part of the meta
system itself as well as at any other
measurable task like benchmarks, the the
benchmarks that I showed you at the
beginning um and customer data, things
like this. Uh so talking about uh what
we um
you know empirical results here our most
recent empirical results we have this
blog post that uh where we pointed out
that benchmarks are dead for us and what
this is really referring to is uh not
that benchmarks aren't useful but uh
that in the presence of a properly
recursively self-improving system uh
bench static benchmarks have fairly
limited value because it is uh we are
able to fully automatically
uh uh get soda results, state-of-the-art
results on uh you know, every benchmark
we've we've turned it on. Uh and so
again, as I said, uh fully
automatically, so zero human
interventions and usually quite quickly.
Uh so concretely, here's a table, bunch
of results. Uh the the interesting thing
or one of the interesting things here is
that uh on half of these benchmarks uh
which are across a wide variety of
different um uh different domains that
we've never worked on before uh we got
soda uh using older cheaper models uh
than you know the whoever held the
previous soda and typically Fable 5. Um
so uh what's next after now that uh
we're not focusing on benchmarks uh we
are working with with early customers um
in a variety of a variety of domains. Uh
and I want to leave you uh with just
this perspective on the frontier uh that
the the next phase transition in AI is
going to come from a system that invents
its own improvements. And so at PUDK,
we're we're intentionally casting a very
wide net for that phase transition again
by taking this optimization perspective
on RSI and using it to optimize
everything including the optimizers
themselves. Uh thank you. And we're
hiring.
And now we have Yu CEO of Neocognition
speaking on intelligence. Continue
learning equals expertise.
>> Check.
>> Right. Perfect. All right. Uh so today's
talk will be quite conceptual. Um I will
talk about three concepts. Intelligence,
expertise and how continue learning
bridges the two. Um but I think this
this perhaps one of the most important
conceptual question we need to think
about today and uh it can help explain
many of the bizarre uh observations
we're having at the AI frontier. The
first observation is that u um AI has
gotten so uh so intelligent like the
this morning open just came out with
solving 10 other major mass problems but
on the other hand uh their diffusion in
the enterprise world seems much slower
than everyone expected. Uh and uh we are
seeing an explosion of these four
deployed engineers and deployment
companies to help diffuse AI. But if
these a AI are so smart, why why we need
uh FDs to deploy them? Shouldn't they
deploy themselves, right? Um the like
humans don't need an FD to teach us how
to do a job. So what what's missing
here? And then also like why if we look
at the value acrewance uh in the uh as
stack like 90% of the value is going to
the infra and the model layer and the
application layer is getting like less
than 10% and also often running at a
negative margin. So why is that and
obviously this is not like a stable
equilibrium for the ecosystem. So how
can we solve that? Uh so I think
hopefully this talk will help like
explain many of these bizarre
observations today.
All right. So obviously um agents and
particular we call the current
generation of agents language agents
because the language use for reason and
communication is their defining traits.
Um and they already found their first
mass market which is obviously encoding
and the best way to see that is through
the revenue ramp of anthropics right
everyone has seen this uh magical story
um but coding is the first mass market
largely because it's already a language
village world right everything is
already represented symbolically and uh
well uh very well recorded and
maintained uh so that makes it perfect
for language agents. But what if we
leave the privileged world of code?
Well, not so much not so well yet. Uh I
think then the the Netherland project uh
like uh reported that um we are having a
lot of issues with um deployment of AI
in enterprise. Um, of course this was
from last year and of course the you can
argue about the 95% the number but it's
I think it's a directly directionally
correct about the difficulties and then
we saw all of the bizarre uh failure
modes of agents um and to a degree that
last year went on the uh dash podcast to
to argue that this uh 2025 was not going
to be the year of agent but it's going
to be the start of the decade of agents.
uh and he particularly mentioned
challenges around computer use around
continuous learning
right so I think what we're observing
here is a really modern version of the
Maravx paradox so remember the original
version of the uh uh Maravx paradox from
the 1980s essentially says that for AI
it seems that um hard things are easy
and easy things are hard right so
they're particularly good at the
symbolic reasoning tasks like math and
coding but uh uh very uh very
challenging to learn things that seems
effortless for humans like back back in
the 80s is mobility and perception but
now we are seeing the difficulties in
everyday digital work and why is that uh
here's my hypothesis
if you look at the modern society it's
really not just one unified world it
consists of millions of micro worlds
right every profession is different
every company is different Every company
is special. That's why they exists. So
every environment has its unique local
physics. The structures, the
constraints, the affordances, the dynam
dynamics.
It's just too hoggenous and dynamic for
any static model that tries to compress
that into one static representation. So
you have to continually learn on the job
to form specialized expertise.
And then that leads us to the next
chapter that intelligence is different
from expertise
for intelligence. We will focus on the
LRM context. The type of intelligence
that LMS exhibit um then it's the really
the capacity to solve problems. Give me
the problem statement. Give me the
context. I will reason through this
gigantic solution space and find maybe
possibly spin up like hundreds of sub
aents and try to find a solution for
you. But expertise is different.
Expertise is really accumulated and
situated competence, right? It's the
ability to act reliably and efficiently
and with judgment to deliver uh superior
performance on a particular job in a
particular environment. Right? So
hopefully through this the the the
contrast is very clear and then what
really uh does expertise contain? If we
look into the literature from cognitive
science that can give us some insights.
Essentially when we are learning on a
job to form expertise it's the process
of continually forming new mental
representations about that job about
that domain that allow us uh to that
will manifest in multiple different
ways. Um it will allow us to see things
differently. For example, if you're
looking at a very long bug reports from
a crash system, obviously an expert
versus an intern will see things very
differently, right? The expert will very
quickly locate the plausible places of
failure. And then expert can see the
deep structure, not just like a surface
patterns. The experts know that
everything is conditional that for every
rule there are a whole bunch of printing
conditions that you need to learn like
when that rule holds. But you also need
to learn what are the exceptions that
where you can bend the rule uh against
the reality. Um and finally our judgment
and taste which we talk about a lot
lately also come from expertise. So from
this you can more or less think of like
expertise is really a word model right
it's a model of that micro world that
manifests in many different ways that uh
becomes a foundation for our perception
for our reasoning and for our decision-
making
then we can further compare the two but
in the interest of time I think the what
the most interesting here is to compare
like intelligence is in at least the
form of intelligence have are expansive
in nature right it tries to uh tries to
uh look for the context on the fly tries
to expand its search uh and that as a
result it's uh because it cannot
accumulate from the past as a result it
consumes a ton of tokens uh like uh at
Neocognition we're burning like millions
or millions of dollars in tokens um but
Um for expertise it's contractive in
nature right it's about the process of
forming shortcuts forming effective
structures of the domain that will
reduce your search process uh search
space.
Okay. So next I will talk about
continual learning. Um but since I only
have a few minutes so I have to be much
faster. But continuous learning is a
very confusing term. Uh so let me first
try to give a uh a unifying definition.
I think continuous learning is the
process of adaptive compression of
experience into reusable structures for
future behavior. So all of these four
elements are very important. Uh and you
need to answer for when you talk about
continuous learning or see some work in
learning you need to uh understand each
of these four elements what exactly is
being talked about. So what kind of
experience we're talking about how you
are compressing them um and in into what
kind of structure and how you use that
structure for future behavior right um
but the the adapt adaptivity here is
very important that the things you
compress in the past should determine
like how you compress in the future
then that here's the I think the most
important and interesting part of this
talk um this is the relationship between
intelligent
expertise and continue learning. If you
put intelligence as a x-axis and
expertise as a y-axis, you will see that
they are largely orthogonal, right? You
if you can
uh get like more intelligent models, but
if you don't have continuous learning,
then it will become what I call the
world's smartest novice just tries to uh
brute force its way through every
problem using raw intelligence. That's
why everyone's uh token bill is
exploding and different continuous
learning algorithms will essentially set
the slope of your learning.
So if the goal here is to have a very
strong container learning algorithm uh
that give us very strong uh expert
agents and if we follow this setting
then the most interesting future that we
can derive from this is what I call
unbounded expertise from bounded
intelligence. What if there is a
threshold for intelligence, we can call
it escape intelligence that once we
across that threshold plus a strong
continuous learning algorithm, then we
can get almost unlimited expertise or at
least good enough for maybe 90% or 95%
of the jobs in the world. Then if that
becomes true, that means a very strong
bifurcation of the markets. Right? So
the frontier models they will continue
to build like uh more intelligent models
and there will be many use cases for
those but maybe for the 90 or 90% 95% of
the other jobs we don't need more
intelligent models maybe even current
models are good enough what's left is
continuous learning so that will be uh a
very uh interesting dynamics in the
market
okay I'll skip this one these are some
uh open questions questions we can
answer. Uh but just a few seconds to
take a photo
and finally I think the expertise will
be the next dimension for scaling. Um
but for scaling expertise we are not the
goal here is not to replace human labor.
I don't believe in the job displacement
narrative. I think we are in a short
great shortage of expertise. In the
ideal world, everyone want to have
personal health care, personal financial
advisor, personal tutoring and so on so
forth, right? And every company want to
build its own learning loop local human
AI learning loop that where the
knowledge and the IP occur. And finally
if we can scale uh make expertise
abundance then it will lower the
friction for many of the province that
will uh make a lot of new problems
across the threshold of worst doing so.
So that will create a lot of new
opportunities in the society. So I'll
stop here and thanks for the attention.
>> [applause]
>> All right, we have lots to think about
and a lot of information in a short
amount of time. Next, we have Fuang Hong
uh for reasoning as control, adaptive
test time, compute and planning agents.
Actually I think my talk is going to be
towards self-improving agentic systems
and when people talk about
self-improvement oftentimes we frame it
as a model capability. the model can
actually improve his reasoning and then
you know started to actually learn from
his own output and hopefully acquire
some new skills but I think model is
just one layer at the end of the day
it's going to be an ajinky system that
is going to be deployed and there are a
lot of the infrastructure around the
model how the model is actually built I
think that's also a very interesting
layer for us to understand how we can
keep improving these infrastructure And
that could be even more important for
very kind of vertical applications that
you know utilizing language models in
your very own environment in your
corporate in your own application areas.
So now let's talk about what really
happens in agentic system given a task.
Oh okay the standard um slice technical
difficulty. Um so given a task right so
you will be observing uh you know some
kind of uh you know state you know
transitioning from an environment and
then this kind of observation goes
through your thinking process and at the
end of the day you wanted to make a
decision right maybe at every time
you're going to make a decision what is
the best thing to do right now and you
know in order for agentic system work
oftentimes because these tasks are very
very complicated you wanted to decompose
them into different agents, right? and
you wanted to assign roles for them and
then you know probably you wanted to
design some kind of workflow like you
know nowadays I think we call a loop
engineering right so and then for each
of the agent in your workflow and you
know you wanted to decide what is the
action at every time step and in order
to do that you need to do go through a
thinking process oftentimes a train of
thought right for each action decision
the agent has to generate a reasoning
trace
As you can see there is this kind of
hierarchy of decision making during
runtime right so starting from the very
low level of thinking choices and token
control all the way to action control at
every time step of your decision- making
process and then finally in the very
high level workflow control right can
you optimize them and I think today I'm
going to say foundation models are
actually more and more becoming a
runtime decision maker at At the end of
the day, the self-improving agendic
system is you know possible that you can
improve the model capability but you
could also improve the infrastructure
improve how the model is deployed during
runtime across thinking across actions
and also across workflows. So let's talk
about a little bit about what we did you
know think in each of these levels down
there in the thinking process. I think
we started with the steering problem
where you know you have some kind of
reward model and you're hoping that you
can steer your large language model to
align to the specific reward. Of course,
if you're familiar with the math you
would know that you have a closed form
solution and it turns out this closed
form solution gives you a very short
answer to the very complicated question
of alignment which is you know whatever
your base model gives you you just add
an additional steering signal to it. And
this steering signal is nothing but
something related to a trajectory reward
under some specific optimal policy. I
know this is very complicated math, but
at the end of the day, if you look at
what it's really doing, if you're
thinking about next token sampling from
a language, you know, auto reggressive
perspective, you're just looking at the
language models output and then you just
steer it with some kind of external
signal that you can learn from your
corporate data, right? Um, so now you
know the actual discrepancy here and
sorry I mean I promise the slides looked
way better on my laptop but you know in
this situation there is this discrepancy
about you really want to next token
generation. You wanted to steer your
process as early as possible but you
can't not because your reward model does
not really support that. you have a
trajectory level reward model but what
you really want is a early steering
before you actually determine your
thinking process. So what we ended up
doing for example in a work you know
transfer Q star we started to think okay
if you know the reward models are really
not designed for you know scale up uh
you know the every token sampling let's
just you know do the autocomp completion
and use the reward model in the right
way. Of course, this is right, but it's
really really slow. On on an academic
setting with my A6000 GPU, you can see
if you have to generate 500 tokens will
take you 14 hours, which is basically
impossible, right? So, you're doing it
right, but you're doing it way too slow.
So in a very recent work we tried to
improve it by you know actually come up
with like a specific model family of
reward and we essentially designed a
token level reward and significantly
reduced uh the cost by orders of
magnitude and as a result you can see
this is phenomenal because you can do
like you know any runtime steering of
the model. You do not have to train the
model at all. You can even do weak to
strong guidance. You can use a very
small model to get a very huge model and
then you could even do multiobjective
alignment in the sense that if you have
very different objective you can real
time adapt the objective to the specific
user need. So this is very cool but you
know what about the action right so we
talked about steering your thinking
process but at the end of the day your
thinking process is really for service
of your action. So how do you make the
decision? Um well it is an agentic
system right? So you know we often know
that agentic systems are learned using
this called imitation learning which is
essentially distilled from like exp you
know expert demonstration but this you
know oftentimes run into this kind of
stuck loop problem where your agents
will repeatedly try some actions for
many times until termination or you run
out of your token budget. Right? So
that's very sad. So people started to
think can we do some kind of you know
better um smarter ways of think you know
learning through some world model
training and specifically you know
people thought of like imitation or I
mean imitating self-reflection but this
is not actually self-reflection when you
are trying to self-reflect you're not
actually using yourself to reflect you
are actually mimicking some stronger
model which teaches you how to reflect
and it turns out it works better than
imitation learning but it's not really
giving you very satisfying result. So we
did a very simple thing here. We call it
genuine self-reflection. Rather than
actually imitating how stronger models
you know uh think and self-reflect, we
force our yourself to do the reflection
in terms of choosing which action is
better at this time point. And you can
imagine this is actually a world model.
You're trying to build a mental model
about which action is better under what
state. But you're also forcing yourself
to understand why And this very simple
thing you know worked really
phenomenally. You can improve imitation
learning as well as reinforcement
learning. It actually improves
significantly out of distribution um you
know uh out of uh distribution kind of
performance and also you know performs
way better than previous
state-of-the-art. So like this genuine
self-reflection really really helps. Um
and also I think one really cool thing
is that it actually generalizes to a
general reasoning by just understanding
how agents work better in a specific
environment. You can see this you know
kind of critical learning does not
relate to any general reasoning
capability but somehow it magically
improves the general reasoning
capability. So now you know control
decoding can steer how the agent think
um and then act can actually help your
agent understand how to you know under
what state what is the better action.
Now finally I think what's really
exciting is this kind of like workflow
control autonomously decide what are
your you know agent roles and how do you
actually optimize the topology of the
agents you know sort of like the
workflow optimization. So I have a very
simple example here but for the sake of
time you know just basically saying this
is a very fixed workflow for like you
know a gentic safety kind of
application. It works you know really
well. But the question here is can you
actually design you know such a
framework such that you have a meta
designer as the query comes you could
come up with the best agentic framework
the best harnessing that is specifically
for this very specific task. Well can
you do that you know in an autonomous
way right? So people tried to do this
for example they tried this thing called
one for all and they also tried this
thing for one for each. One for all
basically means that you're going to
find the best workflow in the world for
the specific task and then one for each
is that you have to find the
adaptability you know so that you can
design the best flow for each of the
query that comes into you know your
model. So it it turns out we're thinking
about this you know kind of philosophy
of foundation model right so we don't
want to actually do one of these two but
we wanted to say can we actually
premputee the workflow and sort of like
you know during the training time but
then reuse them during the deployment
time and can we achieve efficiency
through that kind of process and it
turns out what we did is we built a bank
we built a bank of workflows and then
during test time yes we're going to just
like adapt to the specific workflow real
time really efficiently and as you can
see the result also worked really well
like you can see significant improvement
of the performance
I can share a better version of the
slide that is actually rendering correct
but you know if you trust me so you will
see like the performance is really nice
so just to sum up you know we talked
about self-improving agent systems. We
talked about how you know there are
three levels of runtime decision makings
that you can be very smart about how to
allocate your compute resource with the
limited budget. How to steer your
thinking process as early as possible so
you do not have to go through the very
lengthy kind of process of thinking but
in the wrong way. How do you control
action? And finally, how do you do the
workflow control? And with that, thank
you.
[applause]
>> Okay. For our last individual speaker of
the day, Raja Giris, professor at Tel
Aviv University on the visual
compatibilities of multimodal models.
>> Hello everyone.
want to thank the organizers and all the
previous speakers for the interesting
talks. Uh my talk is taking a slightly
different angle than what was presented
before. So everyone here was talking
about coding agents and how we can
extend them. Here I want to talk about
adding new capabilities and which is
going to multimodel. So most current
models focus on how to improve coding
because like it's easier to work like
that. But
uh when you hear me now, you don't just
see a text, you see me, you see
everything. So we live in a multimodel
world. And the question is what are the
current visual capabilities that we have
in this in multimodel models. So there
are various challenges when we look at
multimodal models and I think that one
of the interesting thing that we see in
the field is that once people start
asking the right question in one or two
years we start seeing solutions. So few
years ago uh with my group we had some
works on compositional reasoning. There
were some observations that one of the
problems of old multimodel models
when they look at captioning of images.
So for example, if I have
a if I want to generate or want to
describe an image with like three zebras
and two giraffes. So basically all the
numbers and names are mixed together and
the model is treating everything as a
bag of forts. And then there is some
problem with compositionality.
And then with my group we had various
work on improving the group
positionality. And since then things
improved. So we use some tree
structures. We took the words and de
composed them into trees. We basically
had more dense and aligned captions and
basically we taught this model to be
structured. So you can see them in this
works. Afterwards
we found other problems that exist in
these models. So in
two works we try to analyze what happens
if you try to work with these models
and see what happen in the workflow of
understanding. So in one work that was
done uh with my colleagues which is
called performance gap in entity
knowledge and was published in ACL one
year ago we basically try to see where
in multimodel models we can we can see
the reasoning and one of the problems
that we see in current multimodel models
is that basically if you look at all
modern multimodel models you have very
strong LLM and a nice visual head
attached to it. So we invest lot of
resources in training LLMs but then we
have some nice visual visual language
model that we found somewhere we
attached to it. We train them together
afterwards with some post- training and
then when you analyze what happens when
these models try to do some multimodel
understanding you see that most of the
analyzes that happen happen in the LLM
part and not in the visual part.
Another work we try to analyze what
happen if we try to do in context
learning. So in LLMs we know that in
context learning is great but then the
strange thing that we found in VLMs or
multimodel models is that if you give in
context learning that is too long with
too many images basically the models
start to get confused and again the
reason for that is that currently when
we train multimodel models we mainly
rely on the language part and the
question is maybe we need to make a
certain shift. So the focus in my talk
would be on a specific ability of
multimodal models which is special
cognition
and there is an interesting
work of my colleagues that was published
two years ago which is whether special
cognition emerge in frontier models and
what they did is they checked various
special cognition tests on multimodel
models and they checked sometimes ask
like mental rotation. We get a shape and
then we ask which shape is basically the
same shape but rotated.
Another interesting task is perspective
taking. I am asking where the dog what
is for example the angle between the bat
and the dog and then the question is
whether such model can answer that.
Another question is mess completion.
We want to ask a model to solve this
maze. And then another interesting task
is shortcut discovery. In shortest
discovery, basically you show a model a
walkthrough through a place, but you
don't go in the shortest path and then
you ask the model to go in the shortest
path and you check whether the model is
capable to do that. So all of these are
very important
task in in in special cognition. The
interesting thing is that two years ago
all the models were very bad. If you
take the frontier models like GPT and
other frontier models they would act
really bad. But the interesting thing is
that once you start asking the question
you start to see improvement throughout
time. So this work that was two years
ago you get that frontier models are
quite close to chance. They're a bit
better.
January this year there is was an
interesting war called baby vision they
made a similar exploration and then they
found that on January this year the
frontier models were basically at the
level of three-year-old child so from
models that don't know anything we grew
up to three years so the interesting
thing is that you see that once question
is asked sometimes it's more important
to ask the question people start to
pursue that and in one and a half year
we go to three years which is nice to
grow to become three years old in one
and a half year but usually we want to
grow slower. Another
interesting work which is
asked compared how much time it takes
for a human to solve a problem and then
checked compared this time to uh what
the models can do. And basically they
found that current frontier models and
this happened in February 2026 can solve
special cognition tasks that take for us
as human 10 seconds. So if you think
about it like mental rotation me solving
it take us some times to solve. So these
models are able to solve only the tasks
that we are able to solve in 10 seconds
which is not so great but better than
what we had before.
And then if we look at the task that I
talked before. So here we can see the
state of advance since the initial work
I mentioned by my colleagues was
published two years ago till today. So
uh two years ago for example in
perspective taking the best models were
close to chance. Two years after now we
can see that for example OPUS 4.6 and
Germany 3.1 are basically almost close
to 100%. Very impressive improvement in
just two years. In mess completion we
are still not so great but just three
months ago from close to chance we see
that for example at GPD 5.4 before
became very got a great lip and the same
happened with shorter discovery. So we
see that great improvement in these
models and then the question is why this
happens. So in a recent work that I
that in a work that we have done with my
colleagues at Apple we asked the
question of whether multimodal models
imagine electric ship and the answer is
yes. So I don't have much time. I will
just mention briefly and then you can
look at the paper. Basically what we did
we studied various special cognition
tasks and we studied them in an openloop
case. Openloop case mean that we just
show a model the first frame and then we
asked the model to try to solve the game
by giving us what what step it should
do. And the interesting thing is that we
found that if we look at the model that
is not generating any image. It's just
it can receive images but cannot
generate image. And basically we probe
the weights.
We can we can take a transformer
attached to the weights probe it. The
interesting thing that we found is that
the model is imagining internally how to
solve the problem. So in difference
tasks for example if we ask if two
shapes have the same naturality we
basically able to see that the model in
its internal weights is reconstructing
the visual thing that we would do if we
look at two shapes and want to
understand if we rotate them they become
the same. So we found that the model is
doing it in its internal weights and
maybe this is the reason for the great
improvement that we see that models
started to imagine and the same happen
for example if we want to assemble
characters. So we can see that models in
their internal weights assemble
characters and
if we see that a model that is not able
to generate visual thing is able in
internal way to do that. So what we done
we added the ability to the model to
imagine we supervised it to imagine and
suddenly we show we have seen
improvement in performance by adding
this imagination ability. So we have
some more results because of time I will
skip them but the interesting point is
or there are two points I want to
mention one is asking the right question
is very important to advanced science.
Second thing is that if we think about
multimodel models, it's very important
for the models not to focus on text but
also to focus on generating the visual
part and it help the model to improve a
lot. Thank you very much.
And now we have a workshop which is on
open aentic stack building the future of
AI systems with open source open
standards and compostability
composability excuse me by the Linux
edition. We have Matt White uh former
global CTO of AI Linux. We have Ben
Burtonshaw community engineer for
Hugging Face. Daniel Han Chen for
co-founder of Unsloth,
Shang Yang from Radex Arc, and Romeo
Barage uh co-founder for Sky Pilot.
Just flip the switch.
Should we be waiting for prescribed time
before we start or go ahead? Okay.
Because we're running like I think we're
25 minutes behind so far.
>> Oh, I'm not going to project. I'm just
gonna say something.
>> All right. Good afternoon, folks. Uh
we'll get started here. uh and I imagine
some folks will kind of trail in. Um so
thanks for having us today. Here we are.
Uh I'm the former global CTO of AI at
the Linux Foundation. I previously led
the uh PyTorch Foundation as the
executive director and CTO and I'm a
visiting scholar at Columbia University.
Um so before we begin, I would like to
share some thoughts as we are living
through unprecedented times. Um, AI
capabilities are advancing at a pace
that would have sounded implausible only
a few years ago. Models can reason
across long contexts, write and execute
code, use tools and operate software,
and coordinate increasingly complex
workflows. We are entering a world where
powerful models can solve complex
mathematical proofs, generate extensive
code bases and power systems that take
actions in production networks that have
real world impact. So, but exactly at
this moment when AI is becoming more
capable and more consequential,
openness is under genuine pressure. So,
the idea of restricting or even banning
access to open weight models is no
longer a hypothetical, right? uh it's
being actively debated in Washington and
elsewhere and we're also hearing
proposals that can to attempt to control
the frontier through chips, compute,
distillation, safety testing and model
release processes.
The safety and security and national
security concerns behind these
discussions are real and legitimate.
They deserve serious technically
informed responses.
But we must also be equally clear about
the risks on the other side. Blunt
restrictions can concentrate capability,
infrastructure, and decision-making to a
very small number of institutions. They
can transform artificial intelligence
from broadly accessible and general
purpose technology into something that
the rest of society is only permitted to
rent from a few labs. That cannot be the
foundation on which we build the future.
Openness is how we create competition.
It is how researchers inspect systems,
developers adapt them, students learn,
enterprises maintain sovereignty over
their data and stack and countries build
AI capabilities without being
permanently dependent on a single
vendor. So openness is also an essential
part of safety. It enables reproducible
evaluation, transparent interfaces,
independent scrutiny,
shared security tooling, and the ability
to identify and correct problems.
Sorry. Oh, there's no slides. It's just
me rambling.
Um, so, but open communities allow more
people to test assumptions, discover
vulnerabilities, compare approaches, and
contribute to solutions.
But openness does not mean ungoverned.
It does not mean being careless, unsafe,
or a free-for-all. Openness means that
systems can be inspected, evaluated,
adapted, and improved. It means that
interfaces are interoperable,
implementations are contestable, and no
single organization controls every layer
or decides who's permitted to
participate.
This becomes even more important as we
move into agent AI because an agent is
not simply a model. An agent is a stack.
It includes the model, the harness, the
tools it can invoke, the environment in
which it acts, guard rails, the
reinforcement learning systems through
which it improves, the evaluation
infrastructure that measures it, and the
compute on which the entire systems
rely.
An agent may depend on APIs,
credentials, sandboxes, memory,
inference systems, orchestration
frameworks, and multiple forms of
specialized hardware.
It may cross organizational, cloud, and
geographic boundaries while completing a
single task. If any one of these layers
becomes closed and vertically
controlled, the entire ecosystem becomes
less portable, less competitive, and
more fragile. That is why open models
alone are not enough. We also need open
environments so that agentic tasks can
be reproduced and shared. We need open
reinforcement learning frameworks so
that more people can improve models and
agents.
We need open compute layers so workloads
are not captive to one cloud or compute
vendor. And we need open standards so
all of these components can work
together without requiring permission
from a central platform.
The open agentic stack is therefore not
one project. It's not one framework or
one model. It is a shared architecture
built from open source software, open
standards and composable components. And
that is the arc of today's disc of
today's workshop. We will examine four
fun foundational layers of that stack.
Environments, models, reinforcement,
learning and compute. Each talk
addresses a different technical
challenge, but they share a common
principle.
The future of AI should be modular
rather than monolithic, interoperable
rather than captive, and open to
participation rather than controlled by
permission. This is not simply a
philosophical reference. It is an
architectural, economic, and strategic
requirement for a healthy AI ecosystem.
So, thank you for being here and thank
you for contributing to that future.
With that, we will begin with our first
speaker, uh, Ben Burtonshaw.
So [applause]
Ben is from hugging face. Uh Ben will
introduce openend an open standard and
community hub for building sharing and
running agentic environments. Uh these
environments define the tools, APIs,
credentials, execution contexts and
tasks through which agents operate or
sorry learn and operate. Uh Ben will
explain why shared environment
specifications and harness protocols are
essential for reproducible training,
safer execution and collaboration across
the open source ecosystem. So with that,
please welcome Ben to the stage.
Get you set up here.
Hi everyone. So as you heard I'm I'm Ben
from Hugging Face and I'm going to talk
to you about a project called OpenM and
open-source agentic RL environments in
general. My opinion, my hypothesis is
that RL environments are the best way to
democratize AI, the best way to kind of
take a stake in AI. Uh mainly because
they're pretty easy to build. They're
just applications. They're just the kind
of things that we do on a daily basis um
for that reason. Uh and everyone can get
involved. So, I I'll work through this
in a pretty um kind of high level and
and ecosystem kind of perspective and
then uh Daniel's going to kind of go
even deeper on RL and uh and we're going
to go quite far in it. But if I miss
anything, please uh come and ask me
questions afterwards or contact me. So,
what is an RL environment? Right, the
simplest way to explain what an RL
environment is is that it's a world that
an actor acts within or that an agent
acts within. Uh the kind of original RL
environment would be a chess game where
the the board is is the is the world.
The the pieces are are the state of the
the environment. The rules are the the
actions or the moves that the that you
can make within the game and the the
score the game score is the reward. And
in reinforcement learning, we would use
uh that reward to update our agent and
and to learn from that.
So that's just a game. But let's kind of
scale that up now to something a bit
more realistic. So we could take
software engineering. If we say that
software engineering is defined as uh a
task that's that's in a in a GitHub
issue and the the work is in the GitHub
pull request and the the score of that
work are the results of the test suite
and maybe the CI then we would say that
we have an environment that is there for
for software engineering. And this is
how papers like like Swissmith and
others have built software engineering
environments. We could take this and we
could then remove the the work that the
from from the pull request. We could
remove the code from the pull request
and get an agent to generate a code in
that same environment and use that test
suite to get our reward. And then we
have an environment for software
engineering that we could use to train a
software engineering agent. Now we could
carry that archetype across many
different tasks, right? email triage or
say project management and we would need
to find the tasks the reward and the
state within those environments and
build them into applications
and so this is what we're talking about
with uh RL environments okay so what
does the ecosystem look like
so to explain this I kind of like to go
back to something called the matter
cycle if you studied machine learning at
at school you you would have encountered
it it's the model, annotate, train,
test, evaluate, revise,
um, loop and it's not so common nowadays
because it's it's a little bit outdated
for modern machine learning and we kind
of need to update it a bit. So I like to
update it to what I call a capability
cycle. So if we look at a capability
cycle, we would say that we discover
capabilities, we then benchmark them, we
represent them in data and then we train
models on them. Typically we discover a
capability with a harness or or with
some kind of prompt, right? We we elicit
this this capability out of the model
and we can see that okay it is able to
do a certain thing uh maybe not
reliably.
We can then evaluate that capability and
we'll typically use another software
stack for that and we'll have an
evaluation harness that will measure
this capability in the model and how
frequent how reliable it is and and we
can iterate upon that as a community.
Next, we'll want to represent that as uh
firstly as a data set and then
eventually as an environment. And that's
where domain expertise will come into
this. And so companies like Merkore will
do a great job of building reinforcement
learning environments around
capabilities for which they'll go out
and and speak to and hire domain experts
in in the respective domain and and
build that environment that encapsulates
that capability. partially based on on
the the benchmark and but ideally
without any form of form of leakage
between the two and we'll then have a
means that we can train a model on and
so that's when the trainers will come in
another part of the software stack but
also another community right now we'll
have labs that are training models using
these data sets and environments so what
you can see from this kind of capability
cycle is that environments are the kind
of the means with which that we move
capabilities from domain experts into
the models that we use. And once the
models and and and harnesses have these
abilities, then we kind of move on to
the next one and we know that right this
capability is is in the weights as it
were, right?
Okay. So that's a really high level
view. What you'll you'll take from that
cycle is that there are many moving
parts, many different communities all
playing in on the environment and
therefore it's a really important part
of the stack to be open. Right? This is
the means with which that we're
communicating
um capabilities. Like imagine if data
sets were in a closed format, it will
kind of be a it would be a particularly
horrible situation. And that's the the
the goal of open.
So if you look for environments, you'll
typically go to papers and GitHub and
you'll find that they're very
distributed. If you look at the recent
Kimmy K3 paper, it came with thousands
of environments. The Miniaax paper had I
think 10,000 environments. Even the
first deep seat paper had roughly a
thousand environments. And all of these
are implemented in different ways. Some
of them are shared in different ways.
Many of them are um sold and they're not
something that's readily available in
the way that openweight models are.
It reminds me a lot of of kind of being
an MLE back in say 2017 when you would
find weights. you'd find implementations
for models on GitHub and then you you'd
go to Google Drive and you and you'd
find the weights from there and and
nothing is really um exposed and
interoperable in the way that it is
today with with model checkpoints.
So that's the problem and then that
problem kind of compounds when you start
to look at training. Daniel's going to
go into this in more detail, but at a
high level a training process is is a is
a framework, right? We have a library
like TRL or Unsloth that we use to to
update our model based on some kind of
action that it does. And in this
environment, we want to use in this
context, we want to use an agent harness
to perform the task. So let's say it's
the software engineering task. That
agent harness is going to do that and
interact with this environment, use
tools in that environment, and then
we're going to update the model. So each
of these edges, we have a different
layer that that needs to be interfaced,
right? Um and we can't have a harness
that expects a certain environment
definition and we need to also work with
multiple harnesses like pi and codeex
and claw code etc. So the challenge kind
of compounds
the other one of the main mechanisms
that we're working on in openm to get
this to work are environment hubs. So on
Hugging Face, we have about 4,000
environments now that can be pulled in a
standard format that you can plug into
most major training frameworks. There
are other environment hubs like Prime
Intellect and there are also uh more
coming and we're collaborating with uh
orgs to share our specs so that if they
use if they build environment hubs
they'll be able to use a spec such that
they can download environments and share
them uh in an easy way.
So in in code terms like this is what it
looks like to use open m. We imagine
that it would mainly be driven by an
agent but you you could it's a bit like
docker. So you'd say openm in it and you
would get a scaffold of a kind of hello
world uh environment that that just
gives you a generic score and from that
you would just need to write the
business logic to for your environment
or you could generate the business logic
with a with a code agent. You could also
import environments from different
libraries like verifiers and then you
can push, pull and fork environments on
the hub so that you can share them or or
use other people's and adapt them.
That's the the base layer of of OpenM.
And the the features that we're working
on next are to be able to discover
environments from hubs and then to be
able to validate them. So at the moment
the process of finding an environment
for your use case is quite difficult but
if you could search for environments on
the hub you'd be able to pull those and
get a range of community environments
which is quite nice. We can share with
each other and then that creates another
challenge. How do I know which
environment is better? How do I know
which environment is going to help on my
use case? And that's where this new
validate command comes in where we'll
say okay this is a valid spec and also
we'll we can train a small model to see
if it lifts performance on a given
benchmark. So with these two commands
we'll have a an autonomous loop for
these for integrating environments in
post- training.
Okay. So the last block of the talk is
then how can I use an RL environment. So
the the quickest way to get started
would be an evaluation and I'd suggest
that kind of most people do this because
you can represent a typical workload as
an environment and you can see how good
a model is. So you could take a model as
a as weights or or as a just an API and
you could define your environment with a
set of tasks and a reward function and
run the model over that those tasks and
you'd get back an aggregate score of how
good a model is your environment, right?
the the main way or or the core way that
we we would work look at this would be
with reinforcement learning. So we would
take a model or a policy and we would
roll it out over this environment and
get a set of actions and then we would
calculate rewards on each of those
rollouts. We could use an algorithm like
GRPO which Daniel I know is going to
come come into further where we would
calculate the reward for each of those
rollouts and then take a mean across the
whole group and update the weights based
on that mean and then um we'd iterate
like that. So if you're interested in
more detail on this, I've got a few
talks where I go into greater detail on
this, but at a high level this is how
we'd use an an RL environment.
And then in a the next way would be
distillation. So in this setting, you
wouldn't really be able to distill from
from strings like you wouldn't be able
to distill from from tokens. You would
need log probabilities. And we would
take a student and a teacher model. We
would roll out the student. So we'd get
it to generate to perform a task inside
an environment. And we take the log
probabilities of of that student on this
task. And then we would get a teacher to
do the same task or to roll out over the
same token, sorry. And we take the log
probabilities of the teacher on those
tokens and then update the weights of
the student based on the difference the
reverse KL from the student and the
teacher. That's one way. We could do
this in a few different ways. So we
could also take the student and do self
distillation where we say okay um let's
take the best example of the student and
compare it to the average or we could
give the student some kind of privileged
information or or hint. We might get
that from the environment or from a data
set. Like for example, in the pull
request setup, we could say here's the
actual solution to this code and we give
that to the agent at the beginning and
then we update the weights based on the
difference between its bad run and its
good run.
Okay. So that's the core of OpenM.
That's what we're working on. The the
main takeaway is that we're trying to
make it so that open environments can be
shared. uh yeah openly across the the
hugging face hub but also others. And
how do we think that this is going to
work? How do we think it's going to be
effective? The answer to that is is
leaderboards. Like we kind of see
environments at the moment existing in a
bit of a shadow realm. Like they're
they're not really um they're not really
spoken about that much or or they're not
really um seen within within the
community around model releases. And we
think that if people can start to build
their own environments and try them out
and then we put them into leaderboards
and we figure out which ones are are
good and which ones are contributing to
model success then more people will get
involved and and we'll share more of
these leaderboards. So that's the talk.
Thanks Ben.
Thanks.
Thanks. Hello. Thanks Ben. Hello. Is
this working?
All right. So, there it's actually
working now. Okay. Uh, so our next
speaker is Daniel Honchen, co-founder of
Unsloth AI. Uh, Daniel's talk has a
wonderful direct title. Uh, making open
models not suck. Um, open models are
advancing rapidly. Uh, but anyone who's
deployed them in an agentic system has
encountered some practical problems for
sure. uh looping behavior, malformed
tool calls, unreliable formatting, and
failures that compound over wrong run
long long running tasks. Um so Daniel
will examine why these problems occur
and what developers can do to make
models more reliable, efficient, and
genuinely competitive with closed
systems. So with that, please welcome
Daniel to the stage.
>> Hello.
Hello. Oh yes. Okay. Hello everyone. Um
you know thanks for coming today. Um yes
we have oh wait the okay wait let me
check. Um is the oh okay there we go.
Okay. It's a bit awkward the computer
but okay let's see if it works. If the
slides you know fail please tell me. Um
but yeah like hello everyone. I'm Daniel
from Unsolve. Um and great to be here.
Um but today I'm going to be talking
about how to make open models not fail
not suck and how to make it like much
better overall. Um yeah, so for you
folks who don't know us, um we're you
know we're we're on um we are one of the
largest organizations on hugging face.
Um and we distribute models to the
entire world. Um okay, that number is
outdated, but we have around 400 million
total downloads on HuggingFace. We
distribute the largest models and the
smallest models and we're the third
largest distributed in the entire world.
Um so we um you know we also don't just
distribute models, so we also fix bugs
and open source models. So we
collaborate with all the large labs and
hardware providers in the entire world
to fix issues in the models before you
get them. Um so if you're using open
source models on your laptop, on your
computers, they're most likely fixed by
us in some way. For example, you know,
OpenAI's GWSS had some issues. Llama,
Jamma, MRO, all of these models have
some issues. And you know, we're here to
like, you know, help make the models
much better for people to use.
Um recently, most people should know,
you know, Kim K3 has been launched. Um
it's the you know world's best um openw
weight model that anyone can download.
So they just released, you can download
this on hugging face. Um it's quite
large, you know, 1.5 terabytes. Um but
you can download this on hugging face.
It was just released um just a few days
ago on Monday. Um and you know, for what
we did is we quantized it down to one
bit for you to use. Um so it's not, you
know, 1.5 terabytes anymore. It's around
600 GB. Um and Kim K3 was actually 4bit.
Um so it's actually not that easy to
quantize anymore because, you know, 4bit
going to one bit is not that much
savings. Um but we show that you can
retain 70 76 to 78% of accuracy but you
can reduce the size by 82%. Um, so it
doesn't, you know, when you reduce the
size of a model via quantization, you're
not going to make the model, you know,
82% dumber, it's only like, you know, 16
or something% dumber. And we show, for
example, some examples, a one bit KI did
pretty well on some prompts. You know,
this is one bit, okay, versus, you know,
the Kim K3 at uh 4bit, so the full
precision, you know, versus Claude,
Opus, and G uh GBD.
Deep See just released an update
yesterday. Was it yesterday? Yeah, I
think it was yesterday. Um, but
yesterday they released, you know, um,
0731 for Deep Seek V4 Flash. Um, so that
was an interesting release at a weird
time. Um, and then they just randomly
dropped it at some weird time zone. Um,
and so we also quantized it down for
people to use. Um, so you only need to
use 90 GB of re of VRAM or RAM um, for
you to run Deepseek V4 Flash. Um, and it
is I would say it's the best model for
its size. Um, so Kimiki 3 is still much
better, but it's ginormous. Um but
Deepseek V4 flash can actually fit on
your local computer and run it. Um so it
works very very well.
Um so like you know as open source
models and closed source models both of
them are getting better and better over
time. Um for folks I'm not sure if you
have seen the meter plot. So the meter
plot shows um the dub the meter plot
shows how much progress is there in AI.
Um so like for example you can see
Claude the plot is a bit outdated um
because they have not updated it. Um but
you know models can take um models can
do tasks that take humans 16 hours to
do. Um and it can do this very very
well. Um this is a 50% probability. Um
so the 80% probability is a bit less. I
think it's like 6 hours or so. Um but
you can see models are progressing at an
exponential um speed if you log it. So
if you do a linear trend um you can see
that the exponential progress is much
more clear. Um I also plotted you know
mythos or like you know fable as the red
line. Um and also GBD 5.6 soul. Um, so
this actually removes cheating. Um, so
some of these models, they like to
cheat. Um, if you do include the
cheating examples, then GBD 5.6 Soul is
127 uh, sorry, 270 hours. Um, so if if a
human can do a task that takes 270
hours, GBD 5.6 can also do it. Um,
however, that's probably not a good
example. So if you remove all this
cheating examples, um, it's around 16ish
hours. Um but you can see over time that
models are improving at a dramatic pace.
If you look, if you squint a little bit,
you know, if you squint a little bit,
there is actually this horizontal line
area, right? So, if you can see around
2023 to 2024ish,
um there is actually a plateau
approximately um if you can squint a
little, right? So, GBD4 to GB40, there
was not that much progress. Um and the
main reasoning behind this is because
reinforcement learning and um reasoning
was not invented during that time. Um
and so if you plot two different plots
like line plots um a trend if you just
plot you know the non-reasoning time
frame versus the reasoning time frame
you can see that if we did not invent
reasoning so 01 if 01 preview if open AI
did not like you know tell everyone you
can do reasoning then AI models would
have plateaued um and so if you can see
the gray line if you just plot you know
if you just fit a trend to the models
before the reasoning age all models
would have plateaued by now um and the
doubling time. So if you so every single
seven months the models will get double
in capability. Um that was the olden
days. Um but now the green trend is when
you add reinforcement learning, you add
reasoning and you can see the doubling
time has shrunk to 3.5 months. So this
means you only need to wait 3.5 months
for the model to be double in
capability. Um so you know Opus 5 just
got released a few days ago. Um wait 3.5
months and you'll get even an even even
better model than Opus 5. Um but
remember the trick is if the trend
continues right so that's the
fundamental um question will the green
line continue and continuously keep
increasing for AI capability um or we
will go we will go back in time and go
to the you know the gray line again
right will AI just like slow down and
slow and then we have to like reinvent
something new again so this is a
question that we will see in our
lifetimes so you know all you need to do
is wait a few months and we shall see
right so like if you models are
plateauing um then this means AI has
plateaued um so all you need to do is
wait 3.5 months to 7 months and we shall
see the trend
so there is another very cool plot for
artificial analysis um so they show open
models versus closed source models um
and you can see the so the blue line is
open source models um and the black line
is closed source models and if you see
very closely open models have very very
closely reached closed source models um
a better a better like indication I you
know I'm not you know my favorite gauge
if you want to like look at one
benchmark you know don't just look at
SWE bench or deep SWE or whatever your
favorite benchmark is my favorite one is
actually weird ML so if you search on
Google weird ML this one is my favorite
benchmark and the reason why it's
actually very hard to game um and you
can see the blue line is open models and
the green line is closed models um
according to weird ML fable uh fable 5
is pretty good um it's very expensive um
so I would suggest you to use opus is
five high which is according to weird ML
the best for its cost and accuracy. Um
but for open models Kimik3 is extremely
powerful. Um you can see for example
they also plot the accuracy across
models. Um so Fable 5 okay that has the
highest accuracy at max reasoning but it
is very expensive. Um it's ginormously
expensive. Um the next one is Opus 5 max
opus 5 high and so on. And you can see
Kimik 3 um is also on the leaderboard.
Um so open models are definitely
catching up.
In fact, if you squint a little bit at
the plot, so this is a bit delayed. If
you squint a little bit at the plot,
there is actually the delay as I was,
you know, talking about 01 preview and
open models. Um, and so this delay is
what we call the open source drought,
which was around 1.5 years ago. Um, and
in fact, if you take the closed source
models minus the open models, you have
this trend. Um, which is the progress of
open models. Um, they're closing the
gap. Um, this this line had is a bit
outdated. Um, so it's more like two
months delay. Um but you can see that
you know with the invention of
reinforcement learning and deepseek
publishing how to do gpo with you know
deepseek R1 um open models then again
went back to trend um and so in fact if
deepsec1 did not publish gpo open models
will be 16 months behind closed source
models but now it's only two months
behind
and you know there is this good blog
post showing a you know trend extra
extrapolation um by 2026 December so in
a few months we shall get an open model
that is as good as a closed source
model. Um but you know this is all
trends so you know who knows if this is
going to happen. All we need to do is
wait a few months and we shall see. Um
and so we shall see if open models can
in fact um be as good as a clos model by
December 2026.
Um another trend I don't know if you
guys saw um do you know open AI
decreased prices of GBD Luna by 80% um a
few days ago. This might sound very
shocking but actually it is not. Um, and
you can see on the deep suite, I don't
know if folks use the deep suite
benchmarks, um, but the deep suite
benchmark shows that GBD 5.6 Luna is
extremely extremely efficient, cheap,
and also very smart. Um, and so, you
know, the plot, the Deep SWE plot is,
you know, to the right to the top is the
best. Um, and so you can see GBD 5.6
Luna has dramatically shifted the um,
line. Um, and so the main question is
token prices are plummeting, but is this
reasonable? You know, people are
thinking, okay, maybe OpenAI is just
shedding all that money. you know why
can deepseeek charge you know 10 cents
versus you know other providers charging
$1, right? Is this actually correct? Um
so actually I did a calculation over the
before the talk um and so if you I don't
know if you folks know um semi analysis
they released something called inference
X and benchmarks for um VLM SG lang and
other inference engines on Nvidia GPUs
and AMG GPUs um and according to their
benchmark Deepseek V4 Pro so the biggest
one um on one GPU one B300 uh B300 GB300
you can do 13k tokens throughput um if
If you calculate this, that means 1 hour
you get 47 million tokens. Um, if you
saturate the GPU, 47 million tokens.
Then if you look at the price of GB300,
it's around $5 per hour approximately
per GPU according to a semi analysis,
right? $5 approximately. Um, and if you
calculate this, right, you can do 47
million tokens per hour, you know, $5
divided by that. That means that
Deepseek V4 Pro, the minimum floor price
is 11 11 cents per 1 million tokens.
And what does deepseek charge? Deepseek
charges 44 cents per 1 million tokens
and 87 cents per 1 million tokens
output. So this means that if you run
deepseek v4 approximately it's not a
loss, right? It's not like openai
shedding money or like deepseek is
shedding money in terms of running these
models. And that is why OpenAI can
reduce the price of GBD5.6 Luna 220
cents and $120. Um and why assuming GBD
5.6 Luna is the same size as Deepseek
V4. Okay, it's most likely not, but it's
assuming it's the same size, then open
AI still raises some money around $1 per
1 million output. Um, if you extract
also Kim K3, so Kim key3 is a, you know,
a new architecture, it's still not very
optimized, but if you look at semi, you
know, semi analysis's analysis, um, Kim
key3 takes around 5k tokens throughput
per GPU. Um, so it's around 2.6 times
um, less than deepseeek. Um, and if you,
you know, according to Kim K3, I don't
know if you guys use the model, it is
$15 per 1 million output. Um, that is
extremely expensive. And why? Because
the, um, if you divide it, um, so it's
actually 29 cents. The floor price for
Kim K3 is 30 cents per 1 million tokens.
Um, so Kim K3 is get so Kim Moonshot and
the other inference providers are
getting $14.17
on your API cost. Um so if they wanted
to reduce price they can all the way to
30 cents. Um obviously well you know you
still need some revenue and some profit.
Um so the price of these models are
still slightly inflated and deepseek is
the only one which is charging you know
at close floor prices for their models.
Um you know another plot that I really
like to look at is Arena. So Arena has
this like para efficiency plot. Um you
know you know folks probably looked at
arena scores and stuff like this. I
don't really like the arena score but
the good way is to look at the par
efficiency plot that they publish um and
you can see that you know so to the top
to the right is always the best um as
normal um but you can see there is a lot
of models that are in this you know par
efficiency line and you know for the
performance that you want you should
look at which model you want to use um
and so many open source models are also
on the par efficiency front um for web
development um so you know if you want
to do HTML development web development
and stuff like that Um, you know, Opus 5
Max for now is the best. Um, however,
Kim K3 is just behind it. Um, so if you
want to use like a, you know, slightly
cheaper model, um, and, you know, if you
want to, you know, um, have still very
good accuracy, Kim K3 is a very good
model. Um, GLM 5.2 is also on the, you
know, on the plot and other models. Um,
but you know, if you don't want to pay
API cost, there is another way. You can
run the models locally on your computer,
right? And the cost becomes zero, right?
Not any cost, just electricity cost.
Okay, some setup cost, some you know
front loaded cost. Um but yeah,
essentially that is what we do.
Essentially we can reduce a model size
to very very small bits like one bit by
using dynamic quantization. Um and you
know we show many many Twitter posts
about this you know we did it for GLM,
we did it for Kimmy, we did it for many
many many other models. Um so if you go
to our hugging face page you know you
can download these models that you can
run locally on your computer. Um some of
them are very big. So, you know, Kimi is
still 600GB.
So, you know, I'm not sure if that can
run on your computer. Um, but you know,
we're trying our best to like reduce it
to like one bit. Um, and even below one
bit, you know, how can we make Kimi
like, you know, 250GB, for example. Um,
for example, a very good example is GLM
5.2 one bit. Um, you know, you can see
this is oneshotted prompt. So, we didn't
like, you know, tell it to like edit
bugs or, you know, fix bugs and stuff
like that. And you can see that GLM 5.2
who does very very well compared to the
other um closed source models. Um and
remember this is one bit versus full
precision. Um so this is not like some
full precision model. Um we also showed
you know perplexity benchmarks you know
to show you that one bit works well. Um
Ko divergence. So another way to
benchmark these models is to use KO
divergence. Um and yeah. So oh wait, how
much time do I have left? Or is it Oh,
okay. Uh I shall skip this then. Um okay
I will skip this. Okay the last thing
I'm going to talk about is ARC AGI. So
you know folks if you know um you know a
few days ago OpenAI posted that in order
to make models good um they show that
the ARC AGI benchmark is actually a bit
bad for GBD. Um and the reason why is
because they had a rolling truncation of
175k tokens. Um and they did not enable
compaction and they did not enable
preserve thinking. And if you just
enable these two flags, you can make
OpenAI's models increase all the way to
40% accuracy. Um, you don't need to do
anything. Just enable compaction and do
preserve thinking and you will get high
accuracy. Um, and I was going to say
like other stuff like, oh, whatever.
There's not enough time. [laughter]
We have some slides. I'll post some
slides off, but um, yeah, thank you for
listening, I guess. Um, yeah.
[applause]
>> Thanks, Daniel. All right, so next up we
have Shangyang from Radics Arc
introducing Miles, a flexible and
scalable reinforcement learning
framework for enterprise facing agent
training.
Uh, okay. Good afternoon everyone. Uh,
thanks for the invitation. Uh my name is
Shan and I'm a research resident at Radx
and a PhD student at MIT. So today I'm
very glad to uh introduce mouse to you
guys on behalf of the team. And to begin
with mouse is a production facing system
for reinforcement learning frontier
language models for with very fast speed
and stability. And today we will first
uh uh give you a very brief overview of
the overall architecture of mouse and
then highlight some recent new release
and new features of the mouse systems.
So let's dive in
and first of all uh the first question
is what is mouse and it is an open
source IO engine for frontier models
developed by radxark and the key uh the
key point for mouse is that it's a
stable efficient and reproducible
reinforcement learning system at scale.
So you can minimize the effort to run a
reinforcement learning job on you know
uh you know modern language models with
uh different kind of environments and
different kind of reward designs.
So at a high level there are three
layers in mouse. Uh first of all is we
have a SG as a robot engine which is uh
specialized for high throughput uh
monitor generation and it's also very
compatible with uh nowadays agentic
agentic system agentic environments and
agentic info and in the middle we have
the orchestration layer which organize
everything like a robot engine and
backend training systems as as a whole
so you can uh makes our system run uh
very efficiently and finally we have
different for different kind of training
engines such as Nvidia action and FSTP.
So uh it's also very flexible and you
can customize your own training engine
on your like own computer uh computer
resource
and here are a key picture of the MOS
architecture. So on the left we have
robot engine which uh generate
trajectories by interacting for example
with the external environment um or an
agent framework and SGLon provides a
generation layer. So while the
environment itself can be very
customized or alternated uh based on the
customer's you know uh requirements and
the in the middle the system turns the
trajectories into some uh rewards some
loss functions etc. So you have the
training signals and finally we have the
as we mentioned we have the maxron or
fstp as the training back end. So you
can uh update uh doing the forward and
backward and computes the loss and
updates of model weights and finally
this model weights will be synced back
to the inference engines raw engines. So
the whole pipeline can uh run in the
circle
and why we use SG as a raw back end.
There are some uh just some advantages.
Uh first of all it's co-evolved with ARO
workload. So including the partial raw
support and uh we can have dedicated ro
control. So it's very uh easy to have
your workload specified. And second uh
it's raw designs uh its router design is
very high performance. uh for example
you can have a very well designed cache
well load balancing for high stroke
generation and it's also natively
supports asynchronous generation with
training engine which is a very
important feature in nowadays
reinforcement learning algorithms and
it's also fast moving and uh uh fast
moving and there are a lot of
optimizations for examples as SG for
speculative decoding with mouse so you
can use speculative decoding during the
real stage of reinforcement learning
And here are some um key points that why
mouse can change IO develops workflow.
So as we mentioned before the first
thing is that it's customizable. So we
can support different kind of workloads
uh just with some customizable function
pass. So it can be very easy to define
your own IO workloads and your own like
reward function and as update method and
it's also modularized and modularized
and non-invasive. So it can be very easy
to change to different uh training back
ends for example as we mentioned FSTP
and max and we will also support
different kind of training back ends in
the near future.
And here are some more technical details
about the system design. So first of all
we have the uh route engine uh and we
support multi agentic route as we
mentioned a lot of times before and
specifically we support token in token
out uh tito for short which is uh that
which means that we don't need to do the
dec tokenize and detokenize again and
again for the same multi-turn generation
so it can save a lot of uh cost and also
makes the Chinese more stable and we
also have three fore models which means
uh route routing replay so when training
ro training models with ARO. So you
don't have to worry about like the
replay kind of things which means that
for different runs you have different
router a different expert routed for the
same uh for the same request. We don't
want that. So we have the R3 to make
sure that it's fully reproducible.
And on the training side in uh we also
support low precision such as end to end
MXP8 support and we also support them uh
per token MVIP for quantization for the
road stage uh so that it can uh greatly
uh decrease the Chinese decrease the
Chinese latency and increase the Chinese
throughput and all these kind of things
has been verified in the uh our latest
uh blog uh with the real world training
workloads and we also have the Laura
support for resource constraint uh
scenarios so that you can train large
model with a smaller number of GPUs
and here is the current support metrics
of the mouse. Uh we recently uh launched
the day zero report uh day zero support
for newest models such as Kim K3 the
inkling from sinking machines lab and we
also support like deepseek v4 natron
ultra etc and we also have a wide range
of precisions as we mentioned and also
wide range of hardwares and more
importantly uh we support uh different
kind of uh fetuning recipes not only is
the SFT RL we also support OPD on policy
distillation
And we have uh verified the mouse
framework with over 10,000 GPUs for IO
training workload. And we accelerate the
IO training throughput. Like for
example, for Kim K 2.6, we can uh speed
ups the generation throughput to one uh
to 12 uh to 12.5k output tokens per
minute per GPU. And we also have
optimized the stability such as the R3
tit as we mentioned and the precision
align training which uh help us to
decrease the training inference mismatch
and we also supports for tolerance
recovery and we support different kind
of uh system uh like cluster back end
such as ray on kubernetics slurm and
bare metal etc.
Uh and finally I'd like to mention some
of the our recent releases like day zero
support for Kim K3 which is nearly a
three trillion parameters model and we
do the finetuning for with mouse on like
different kind of tasks such as the uh
the amass problem. So we uh through the
aretuning we can increase the accuracy
from 40ish to 70 76%.
And for the inkling model from singing
machines lab which is uh also a one
trillion level parameter model uh we use
the full parameter finetuning and the
Laura finetuning and we can we also
optimize the Laura adapter sync
synchronization which means merge the
Laura rank into the uh SGA inference
engine. So this kind of things we
optimize it from almost 50 seconds to uh
less than three seconds.
And finally we have a recent blog post
about mixed precision training as we
mentioned before. So uh we verified that
with different kind of uh precision
choices such as MX, FF8 or MVIP4 we can
uh maintains accur models accuracy and
stability during training and we can
also uh fundamentally and accelerate the
road speed and Chinese speed by a great
margin. Yeah, I think that's all about
uh today's presentation. Thank you very
much for patience.
[applause]
Thank you, Sham. All right, our final
speaker is Raml Bardage from uh he's a
co-founder at of Sky Pilot. So, Ramal
will make the case that AI needs an open
compute layer. Uh please welcome Ramal
to the stage.
All right, there you go. Uh, cool.
Thanks everyone. Um, I'm Romel, one of
the co-founders of the SkyPower project
and today, you know, we heard really
good talks about open environments, how
to do RL in an open manner. Um I want to
make the case that uh there's a need for
a open compute layer for AI uh and
specifically something that sits between
your workloads and the actual GPUs where
your workloads run.
So building AI infra is really hard
right and let me walk you through it
from OpenAI's perspective. You know back
in 2016 uh they signed an exclusive
agreement with Azure to have Azure as
the exclusive provider for the GPUs. Um
but in 2024 um they signed yet another
deal with Oracle uh for $10 billion to
get more more compute and only just a
year later they signed another 11
billion deal with core to get even more
GPUs right and even that's not enough
like you can see Sam Olen tweeting about
like hey we need more and more GPUs just
give us a call if you can like secure
more GPUs for us.
So if the most capitalized company on
the planet right now cannot secure
enough GPUs and if they're not able to
get it in a single cluster, there's a
good chance you also probably cannot do
that right now. And so this GPU crunch
is very very real.
And if you look at the typical AI
organization today, you know, it
typically you have a AI team which has
say some NeoCloud reservation. uh maybe
uh they signed like a two-year or
three-ear deal with one of the neoclouds
when hyperscalers didn't have capacity.
Um then they added some on demand
instances maybe from the hyperscalers
just to supplement that capacity.
Uh but then they also end up having some
kind of on-prem clusters maybe for
regulatory reasons or they just want to
keep data onrem
and then you have customers in Europe so
you need to spin up clusters in Europe
as well. So you need to maintain another
cluster there and then finally you need
a ton of CPUs to run your environments
and sandboxes and for that you need to
maintain another CPU cluster.
So each of these is sort of a decision
made at a point in time where it made
sense to do that but now you end up with
this like big collection of clusters
that you're now responsible for managing
right
and in some sense reinforcement learning
makes it worse right uh it makes it from
uh it it makes it a scheduling problem
because if you think about reinforcement
learning today it's really it is this
whole thing is one job but uh you can
see it's composed of many subcomponents
so for example you can See the trainer
itself needs a lot of VRAM needs many
beefy GPUs but at the same time the
rollout server the one which is actually
generating the trajectories um needs to
doesn't need as much VRAM but needs a
ton of them so that it can like uh
generate lots of trajectories
and then finally to actually execute for
example if you're doing like code
generation models uh your sandboxes need
like a ton of CPUs in parallel to uh uh
run all the trajectories and you also
need very fast old charts on them.
So the question then becomes like why
not just use existing solutions right
like cluster management has been we
we've been doing it for a long time so
why not just use slur or kubernetes
right slowmo is pretty good I mean built
two decades ago from the HPC world and
really you know built for advanced
scheduling capabilities one of the best
I would say you know kota and priority
management systems out there uh but it
really doesn't support isolation in the
form of containers yes you can bolt on
like pyroot and uh uh um more container
you know layers on top of slum but it
wasn't really designed for it uh and it
wasn't really ever built for serving so
it was more for like batch jobs.
Kubernetes on the other hand came on the
scene about 10 years ago uh really
popular for microservices uh you know
and it's very very elastic and sort of
built for the cloud in some ways but has
like a super steep learning curve like
if you hand Kubernetes to a researcher
they'll be like how do I work with this
they'll just probably just have to go to
their agent to make it work um and it
also doesn't have lot of primitives that
are needed for AI specifically around
like gang scheduling again those are
bolt on through like schedulers like
volcano and so on u but It's really hard
to make Kubernetes work for AI. But more
importantly, both are like single
cluster managers. So they still don't
pro solve the problem of like, hey, I
have like 10 different clusters running.
Uh, how do I manage them? Right?
So what's really missing is not a better
scheduler, but something to manage all
these different schedulers and platforms
that you have today. Right? So the goal
is not to replace Kubernetes or slum.
they are really good at what they do but
rather you want to bridge this gap where
you have some workloads like you know
training serving sandboxes that you want
to run on your compute which is
fragmented across like kubernetes slur
and so on
and so the idea is if we can have open
unified compute layer right which can
optimize availability figure out what's
the best place to run your jobs handle
their execution and so on and do this in
a way where your workloads don't need to
sort of know what's under the hood
uh that that would add like a lot of
value to the ecosystem
and that's exactly what we've been
building at uh Skypet you know it's a
completely open source platform uh to
use AI compute wherever wherever you
have it and the idea is you bring your
own framework right so you bring ray
pytor openn uh unsloth your your own
frameworks right and then you submit
them to skypal saying that hey I need
eight b300s for example to run this
And then Sky pilot takes care of the
orchestration, right? Uh it looks at
your compute, your Slim clusters,
Kubernetes clusters, even cloud VMs and
then takes care of like orchestrating
those resources, running the jobs,
getting you the logs, results, etc.
And you know, Sky Pallet started a few
buildings away from here in the soda
hall uh here at Berkeley. Um open source
uh pretty active and healthy community
of uh you know, people using it and
contributing to it. also used by some of
the biggest companies out there right
now. Uh and also it's kind of rooted in
the research we did uh back in the sky
computing lab.
So just a really quick walkthrough of
like how what exactly is Sky Palot, how
does it work? Um you know it's super
simple. Uh the simplest way to get some
resources in Sky pilot is just to say
hey Sky launch uh give provide what
infra you want to run it on and then
state what GPUs you need. If I need to
switch over from say Kubernetes to AWS,
it's just like changing one flag. Uh
similarly for GPUs, uh again your
application needs to be aware of what's
running under the hood. Uh but you can
easily switch what GPU type is
provisioned for you by just changing one
flag.
Um and then if you want to do more
complex stuff, right, like not just
provision some GPUs, but actually have u
a complex job like a reinforcement
learning run, you can. We we have this
abstraction called job groups where it's
a declarative spec. So you say that hey
uh I have a rollout server which needs
these resources needs to run these
commands. U then I have to spin up say a
thousand sandboxes to run the stuff. uh
I also need to for example uh have uh
the rollout server running on H100s
compared to the trainer which may be
running on B200s and then it just passes
over to Skypilot and then Skypilot takes
care of like the orchestration of this
entire workload for you and in doing so
it also provides some nicities like for
example it'll provide you service
discovery uh life cycle management you
know if one of the jobs fails it doesn't
mean the entire run needs to fail it'll
just like restart that job for
Cool. Um, so we've been talking about
training, but serving is equally
important and uh, serving also benefits
from having a unified platform like
this. Uh, specifically you gain uh,
capacity across all your clusters. So
instead of having to launch say one case
serve instance in one cluster, you can
have uh, Skypilot running inference
across all your clusters. And when a
failure happens, right, like Skyfire can
seamlessly move over your replicas to a
region where they where you still have
capacity.
And one of the other benefits of sort of
like having all your workloads run
through one layer is that you can
actually do very interesting stuff by
running both inference and training
together on the same compute. Right? So
the idea is you use the same GPU, same
giant cluster to run your jobs but for
example if the inference requests start
spiking up you Sky pilot can dynamically
reallocate your resources from training
to inference. So it preempts the
training jobs um your checkpointing
logic takes care you don't lose data and
then when the inference spike dies out
it will automatically scale down
inference again and then continue
training.
Cool. And I just want to reemphasize all
of this is B by right. So it's not like
uh Sky Pilot gets you or like you don't
give your credit card to Sky Pilot to
sort of like buy compute. You bring your
own compute from your cloud provider,
your own data. Everything runs on your
own premises.
So you know um I I'll end here but like
really quickly uh the idea is we we
don't need to reinvent or like we need
to we don't need to replace Kubernetes
or Slum. They're really good at what
they do. What we really need is a
unified layer which sort of like allows
you to bridge the gap between your
workloads and all those clusters that
you're running. Um, cool. With that,
I'll stop here. Thank you so much.
[applause]
>> Thanks, Romeo. All right. Well, that
does it for us today. Thank you
everybody for hanging out, sweating it
in the room here, and uh uh thanks for
your support on open source.
I believe we have reception downstairs
for those who are interested. Thank you
everyone.